<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fulfordo et Fulfordae A sermon preached at Exeter, in the cathedral church, the sixth day of August commonly called Iesus day 1594. in memoriall of the cities deliuerance in the daies of King Edvvard the sixt. Wherein is intreated of the goodnes of God toward man, and of the ingratitude of man toward God. By Iohn Charldon, Doctor of Diuinitie. In which also some fewe thinges are added, then omitted through want of time.</title>
            <author>Chardon, John, d. 1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107731</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843427</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843427</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 952:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fulfordo et Fulfordae A sermon preached at Exeter, in the cathedral church, the sixth day of August commonly called Iesus day 1594. in memoriall of the cities deliuerance in the daies of King Edvvard the sixt. Wherein is intreated of the goodnes of God toward man, and of the ingratitude of man toward God. By Iohn Charldon, Doctor of Diuinitie. In which also some fewe thinges are added, then omitted through want of time.</title>
                  <author>Chardon, John, d. 1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Danter: and are to be sold by VVilliam Barley, at his shop in Gratious streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preached at the request of Thomas and Ursula Fulford.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FVLFORDO ET FVLFORDAE.</p>
            <p>A <hi>SERMON</hi> Preached at Exeter, in the Cathedrall Church, the ſixth day of Auguſt commonly called <hi>Ieſus day 1594. in memoriall of the Cities deliuerance in the daies of King</hi> EDVVARD the ſixt.</p>
            <p>Wherein is intreated of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <hi>of God toward Man, and of</hi> the ingratitude of Man toward GOD.</p>
            <p>By IOHN CHARLDON, <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which alſo ſome fewe thinges are added, then omitted through want of time.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 127.1.</hi>
               </bibl> Except the Lord keepe the Citie, the keeper watcheth in vaine.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Iohn Danter: and are to be ſold by VVilliam Barley, at his ſhop in Gratious ſtreete. <hi>1595.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the worſhipfull Maſter Thomas Fulford Eſquire, <hi>loued in the truth, of all that haue known the truth, for the truths ſake:</hi> Mercie, peace, and loue be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV had from mee (which you deſired) the Sermon preached at Exeter in comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of the Citties deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or at the leaſt you receiued the very ſumme &amp; ſubſtance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which I ſuppoſed might haue contented you, and the zealous Gentle-woman your wife, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further adoo: but finding you and hir greatly inclined to vulgar profit, and to make common vnto many which was then vttred vnto
<pb facs="tcp:8159:3"/>fewe, that ſo the benefit of it might redound alſo vnto many: &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you both to bee ſuch as truely, and ſincerely loue and fauour the holy Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt and the Miniſters thereof, and ſeeing your requeſt to ſtand with ſo good reaſon and Godly purpoſe, and that my Office and function bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth mee to doo all the good I can to the Church of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pe. 5, 2</note> and that willingly &amp; of a ready mind (to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your honeſt deſire and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table meaning) haue ſuffred that poore Exerciſe to bee publiſhed which I doe preſente vnto you as a ſimple New-yeares-gift. Of which if any take benefit, let them firſt praiſe God, and next thanke you, that (according to the rule of Chriſt) will haue the meaneſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents and graces of God, bee they fiue,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25 15.</note> or two, or one; many or few, more or les, deliuered his ſeruants
<pb facs="tcp:8159:3"/>for the worke of his ſeruice, to bee well and profitably employed and occupied, that gaine and increaſe may come thereby,
<note place="margin">Luk. 19.10.</note> and not to bee laid vp in a napkin, or hidde in the earth to the good of none. And ſo beſeeching the Lorde to kindle daily more and more in you and in your good wife many ſuch holy motions of his bleſſed ſpirit, and to eſtabliſh you in euery worde and good worke, I wil commend you vnto him and to his might, who is able both to fulfill whatſoeuer wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in you throgh his riches with glorie in Ieſu Chriſt, and alſo of power to keepe you that you fall not, to the very day that you ſhall be preſented faultles and without blame before the preſence of his Maieſtie with ioy.</p>
            <p>In the meane while, quench not the Spirit, grieue not that holy of God by whome you are ſealed
<pb facs="tcp:8159:4"/>to the day of redemption. I will pray alwaies for you that GOD may ſettle and confirme you, and make you worthy of his calling, that the name of the Lorde Ieſus may be glorified in you, and you in him. Pray you alſo for mee: for I truſt that through your praiers I ſhall the ſooner be giuen vnto you againe. The Lorde bee with you, London the firſt of Ianuarie: 1594.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in Chriſt, <hi>Iohn Charldon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:4"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>AD D. THOMAM FVLFORDVM, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <l>Non mea ſunt quae nune mitto tibi, ſed tua: quare,</l>
               <l>Ne tua detineam, quae tua mitto tibi.</l>
               <l>Quae mea ſi dicas; tua tanta modeſtia fulget,</l>
               <l>Vt, cum parua feram, magna dediſſe putes.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>AD EVNDEM TOTIVS CONCIONIS <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <l>Die mihi; corda virum quae ſic dementat Erinnys,</l>
               <l>Vt. ſpernant magni iuſta colenda Dei?</l>
               <l>Si poteris, narra; quali furor incitet oeſtro</l>
               <l>Pectora, quae perhibent nos ratione regi?</l>
               <l>Bos poſſeſſorem nouit, cognouit aſellus</l>
               <l>Praeſepe et Domini (beſtia tarda) ſui.</l>
               <l>Fuſte nimis rigido quanuis pulcetur aſellus,</l>
               <l>Bosque ſub immenſo pondere preſsa cadat,</l>
               <l>Terga grauata tamen praebent fericuda: magiſtri</l>
               <l>Vtráque ſeruitium bellua victa ſubit.</l>
               <l>Aſt genus electum Chriſti, diuina propago,</l>
               <l>Dura negat tenero colla premenda iugo.</l>
               <l>Aſpectant coeli faſtum tellusque fatiſcens,</l>
               <l>Quae noſtrae teſtes proditionis erunt.</l>
               <l>Aethereae volucres, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eluti Grus, Turtur, Hirundo,</l>
               <l>Brumales norunt annumerare dies.</l>
               <l>At nos quos docuit patris Sapientia ſummi,</l>
               <l>Quos nutrit, paſcit, ſuſtinet, ornat, amat.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:8159:5"/>
               <l>Quos &amp; ab immani Jethalis fauce Leonis</l>
               <l>Seruat, &amp; hoſtiles dat ſuperare manus:</l>
               <l>Nos (inquam) Domini praeſagia non meditamut,</l>
               <l>Temnimus (ah) potius tradita ſcita Dei.</l>
               <l>Obtuſasaures praecludimus Aſpidis inſtar,</l>
               <l>Ne feriant ſophiae ferrea corda ſoni.</l>
               <l>Vaſtorum ſolito bellamus more Gigantum,</l>
               <l>Déque ſua volumus pellere ſede Iouem.</l>
               <l>Nunc vbi turgeſcit nimiá pinguedine corpus,</l>
               <l>Obruit &amp; noſtrum nulla procella caput,</l>
               <l>Bella damus ſuperis: ventoſus pectora faſtus</l>
               <l>(Obliti veteris conditionis) agi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Tu tamen (alme parens) hominum qui fecta gubernas,</l>
               <l>Suſcipe quas moeſto fundimus ore preces.</l>
               <l>Tu gemitus noſtros, noſtri ſuſpiria cordis</l>
               <l>Exaudi ſolitâ pro bonitate, Deus.</l>
               <l>Priſtina (chare pater) nobis peccata remitte,</l>
               <l>Poſtmodo dáque tuis carnea corda, pater.</l>
               <l>Nou caperis fuſo vitulorum ſanguine centum,</l>
               <l>Nec caperis longo thuris honore, pater.</l>
               <l>Te placare ſolet quoniam compunctio cordis,</l>
               <l>En: compuncta damus corda, benigne pater.</l>
               <l>Ne nos abijceas igitur quos dextra creauit,</l>
               <l>Sit nobis charitum candida iuncta cohors.</l>
               <l>Conſeruet ma nos miſeratio magna miſellos:</l>
               <l>Inde tibi nomen mite parentis erit.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>AD EVNDEM.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Diſcito (Fulford)</cell>
                        <cell>Sit tibi Chriſtus.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Iuſſa Iehouae;</cell>
                        <cell>Mens tua geſtit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fronte Serena,</cell>
                        <cell>Scire laboras?</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Pectore puro</cell>
                        <cell>Quomodo poſſis</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Diſcito Chriſtum.</cell>
                        <cell>Viuere ſanctè,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Anchora vitae,</cell>
                        <cell>Sanctáque tandem</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Prora ſalutis,</cell>
                        <cell>Tecta Superni</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fons bonitatis,</cell>
                        <cell>Cernere coeli?</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Vita perennis</cell>
                        <cell>Voluito libri</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8159:5"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Dogmata ſacri:</cell>
                        <cell>Itur ad arces.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Conſule Chriſti</cell>
                        <cell>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>andide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>homa)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Dicta magiſtri:</cell>
                        <cell>Temnito mundum,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Conſule Chriſtum,</cell>
                        <cell>Dilige Chriſtum,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Is tibi pandet</cell>
                        <cell>Dilige Chriſtos:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Voce paterna,</cell>
                        <cell>Praemia Chriſti</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Qua ratione</cell>
                        <cell>Sunt diuturna,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Cuncta gubernes:</cell>
                        <cell>Praemia mundi</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ille docebit</cell>
                        <cell>Sunt peritura:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Te pederecto</cell>
                        <cell>Nunc tibi multa,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Claudere curſum:</cell>
                        <cell>Nunc tibi paucae</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Alta Sionis</cell>
                        <cell>Singula noſtra,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Moenia ſaluo</cell>
                        <cell>Singula nulla:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Scandere greſſu:</cell>
                        <cell>Mors truculenta,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Clauſtra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>onantis,</cell>
                        <cell>Mors fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ibunda</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sydera laeto</cell>
                        <cell>Auferet vno</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Viſere vultu.</cell>
                        <cell>Tempore, duro</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Eſt via Chriſtus</cell>
                        <cell>Parta labore.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Vera ſalutis,</cell>
                        <cell>Omne caducum.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Eſt via ſalua,</cell>
                        <cell>Quicquid habetur,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Tuta, quieta:</cell>
                        <cell>Concidit omne:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hâc licet ire,</cell>
                        <cell>Floris Imago.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hâc penetrare</cell>
                        <cell>Sole micante,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Coelica magni</cell>
                        <cell>Fulua recedit.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Caſtra parentis.</cell>
                        <cell>Vt fugit vmbre,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Haec via munda,</cell>
                        <cell>Lubrica tranſit</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Haec via ſana,</cell>
                        <cell>Gloria ſecli.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Haec via certa,</cell>
                        <cell>Vna manebit</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Haec via paſtus</cell>
                        <cell>Arx paradiſi:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Diriget omnes,</cell>
                        <cell>Caetera fumus.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hâcque beatas</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:8159:6"/>
               <head>AD VRSVLAM THOMAE <hi>Fulfordiconiugem Orthodoxam.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>Vrſula, funeſto flerem tua carmina fata,</l>
               <l>Biblia ſi ſcirem te coluiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e parum.</l>
               <l>Aſt munit contra falſi praeludia mundi,</l>
               <l>Meſſiae pectus pagina ſancta tuum.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>AD EANDEM.</head>
               <l>Lesbia cantabat laſciua poemata Sappho,</l>
               <l>Vrſula coeleſtis clara trophęa Dei.</l>
               <l>Lesbis amica chelyn Phoebo dedit: Vrſula Phoebo,</l>
               <l>Vota feret fido pectore clauſa ſuo.</l>
               <l>Vrſula, Sola Deo tua ſit ſeruire voluptas,</l>
               <l>Gaudia vera putes: gloria ſinis erit.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>AD EANDEM.</head>
               <l>Vrſula, collectos cernis flacceſcere flores,</l>
               <l>Et verno nit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>das deperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe roſas?</l>
               <l>Anglorum ſpectas marceſcere lilia peſte,</l>
               <l>Quae fuerant oculis lilia digna tuis?</l>
               <l>Hinc ſubolere potes quaenam ſit gloria mundi,</l>
               <l>Quae tacitè tenues ſoluitur in cineres.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IT IS VVRITTEN IN the firſt Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Eſaie.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Heare, O heauens, and hearken, O earth, for the Lord hath ſaide, I haue nourished and brought vp children, but they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt me.</p>
                  <p>The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters Crib, but Iſrael hath not knowne: my people hath not vnderſtand.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F theſe you expect the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation and meaning: but firſt let vs pray together that God, <hi>of whome is euery good giuing, and euery perfect gift,</hi> may giue vnto you, eares to heare his worde with frut, &amp; may open vnto me the dore of vtterance, <hi>Coll.</hi> 4.3. to ſpeake the miſterie of Chriſt: that I may vtter it, as it becommeth mee; to his glorie, to your comfort, &amp; to the increaſe of his church.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:7"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall GOD and mercifull father, wee thy poore ſeruaunts preſent our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of thy Diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, entirely deſiring thy fatherly goodnes to graunt that thy worde may take ſuch deepe roote in our hearts, that it may fructifie &amp; bring forth an hundreth, ſixtie, or thirtie folde, ſo much as ſhall ſeeme beſt to thy heauenly wiſedome. And next vnto this, we pray thee (O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to bee gratious and mercifull to thy whole militant Church, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed farre and wide vppon the face of this earth; eſpecially to the two principall members of the ſame,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Tim.</hi> 2.<hi>1.2.</hi>
               </note> England and Ireland. And whereas by thy holy Apoſtle Paul, we are willed to make praiers and ſupplications for all men, for Kings and Princes, and for all that are in authoritie, we humbly and hartily
<pb facs="tcp:8159:7"/>pray and beſeeche thee to bleſſe and preſerue thy choſen ſeruaunt our dread Soueraigne Elizabeth, by thy grace, of England, France and Ireland Queene, defendreſſe of the true, auncient and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith; and in all cauſes, and ouer all perſons within theſe hir Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Dominions, next and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly on earth, vnder thee, ſupreame Gouerneſſe. Bleſſe (O Lord) we beſeech thee, both hir and all hir moſt Honourable Councellors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all domeſticall and forren foes, that thy Church ſo proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly begunne, may bee builded and fullie finiſhed according to the platforme of thy moſt ſacred and holy word. And to this ende wee pray thee alſo (O Lorde) to viſite, comfort and cherriſh with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of thy grace, the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and all other inferior Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to whom thou haſt aſſigned
<pb facs="tcp:8159:8"/>the preaching of thy Law, and the charge of thy choſen, that they may bee found good Stewards o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy will, and true diſpoſers of thy ſecretes; and that by their labours ſanctified of thee, thy poore ſheep which wander and goe aſtray in the vale of darkenes and ſhadow of death, may bee brought home to thy ſheepe ſold vnder one ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, thy ſonne Chriſt, the great ſhepheard of the ſheepe, and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Wee recommende likewiſe to thy fauour and goodnes (O Lord) all the Rulers and Commons of this Realme; that the Rulers with courage and in a reuerent feare of thee (according to the truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them) may carefully and truely iudge thy people at all ſeaſons; and that the Commons in their ſeuerall degrees may liue and abide in Chriſtian duety and
<pb facs="tcp:8159:8"/>obedience toward their ſuperiors, and in Godly loue and charitie one towards another.</p>
            <p>We beſeech thee (O Lord) that (in like meaſure of thy grace) thou wilt vouchſafe to water with the dewe of thy bleſſing the two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Vniuerſities of this Lande, Oxford &amp; Cambridge; that from age to age they may ſend forth Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaleels and Aholiabs filled with the ſpirit of wiſedome, vnderſtanding, and knowledge to worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with all the wiſe hearted, all maner workemanſhip for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Sanctuary, for the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Saints, for the worke of the Miniſtery, and for the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the body.</p>
            <p>And here (O Lord) for as much as we are all thy children, &amp; ſheep of thy paſture, we call vppon thee for all our poore and afflicted bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which by any meanes, any
<pb facs="tcp:8159:9"/>where, do grone vnder the Croſſe for the teſtimony of thy eternall truth, that according to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe it woulde pleaſe thee to giue them the fulnes of conſolation, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and conſtancie, that they may chearfully abide whatſoeuer fierie tryall it ſhall pleaſe thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wiſdome to put them vnto; that both by their life and by their death, thy truth may be ſealed, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt that man of ſinne aſhamed, and the Kingdome enlarged of thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. For theſe and all other thy graces what ſo euer, which thou knoweſt to be needfull and neceſſary for vs and thy whole Church, we make our humble &amp; hearty praier vnto thee our God and father, which art the father of mercies and the God of all comfort, according to that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme which Chriſt thy ſonne our Maſter in his Goſpell hath taught vs. <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8159:9"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT EXETER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſaie, 1. verſe, 2. &amp; 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Heare, O heauens, and hearken, O earth, for the Lord hath ſaide, I haue nourished and brought vp children, but they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt me.</p>
                  <p>The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters Crib, but Iſrael hath not knowne: my people hath not vnderſtand.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words which I haue read vnto you (Men, Fathers, and Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beloued in the Lord) diuide themſelues into two parts: an exclamation, and a complaint. The exclamation is conteined in the firſt part of this ſecond verſe, and is made not vnto men, but vnto the heauens aboue, and vnto the earth beneath. <hi>Heare O heauens,</hi> (ſaieth the Prophet) <hi>and hearken O earth.</hi> For becauſe the Iewes refuſed to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8159:10"/>tread the paths of the Lord, and to walke in his waies: becauſe they were like vnto the ſerpent, the deafe Adder, that ſtoppeth his eare at the voice of the charme, rcharme he neuer ſo wiſelie, <hi>Pſal. 58.4.5.</hi> Therefore now (by the Lords appointment) hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto deafe and dumbe creatures, and ſaith, <hi>Heare O heauens, and hearken O earth.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaide, becauſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude and impietie of men is ſuch, that they will not heare, nor hearken vnto the voice of the Lorde, I will ſpeake vnto the heauens and earth, and the heauens (though they bee farre off) ſhall heare, and the earth (though it be ſtonie) ſhall hearken: for the eares of men that ſhould heare and hearken indeede are out of courſe.</p>
            <p>The Prophet doth not this, as though the heauens and earth did vnderſtande: but to ſignifie and expreſſe the abhominable wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes &amp; impiety of the Iewes, he ſpeaketh vnto theſe inſenſible creatures, which did more obay the will of their Creatour, than did they whom he had bleſſed with reaſon and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Prophet (as in this place) ſo in many other followeth the example of the true &amp; truſtlie ſeruant of God <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8159:10"/>who in the 4. of Deutronomie, againſt the Iſraelites, calleth heauen and earth to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in theſe wordes: <hi>I call heauen and earth to record againſt you this daie.</hi> Meaning, that if they would defile themſelues with ſtrange Gods, that then (if men would not condemn them) the very inſenſible creatures of God woulde beare teſtimonie againſt them and their idolatrie. So in the 32. of the ſame booke, hee maketh them witneſſes againſt them of their ingratitude, and ſaith: <hi>Hearken (ye heauens) and I will ſpeak, and let the earth heare the words of my mouth.</hi> In like manner, the man of God in the firſt of Kings and 13 when he ſaw King <hi>Ieroboam</hi> to ſtand by the Altar in Bethel to offer incenſe, cried out by the commandement of the Lord, not againſt the Prince, or people, but againſt the Altar, and ſaide, <hi>O Altar, Altar, thus ſaith the Lord: 1. Kings, 13.2.5.</hi> and immediately the Altar claue aſunder, and the aſhes fell out from the Altar, according to the ſigne which the man of God had giuen by the mouth of the Lord. So that our Prophet <hi>Eſaie</hi> in this place intendeth no new thing, for he taketh <hi>Moſes</hi> and others for example, who were wont to doo the like: A kinde of ſpeech then moſt vſuall, when as iniquitie hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8159:11"/>the vpper hand, when it is grown to that fulnes of meaſure, that it aſtonieth not onely creatures ſenſible, but alſo inſenſible, and when the hearts of the vngodly are ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they cannot be ſoftned, be the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition neuer ſo gentle, or the correction neuer ſo fearefull.</p>
            <p>But what doth the Prophet require of the heauens and earth? verily to heare and to hearken. <hi>Heare</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>O heauens, and hearken O earth.</hi> The Prophet requireth not a ſlack or a negligent hearing, but a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and careful hearing, fit and conuenient for ſo great a cauſe.</p>
            <p>But wherefore would the Lord haue the Prophet thus to exclaim and crie out to the heauens and earth? Doubtles for two ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cauſes. The one was, that the heauens and earth might be aſtoniſhed at the ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and rebellion of his people. So in the ſecond of <hi>Ieremiah:</hi> becauſe they were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, becauſe they made the Lords he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage an abhomination, becauſe the Prieſts taught not the people to ſeeke the Lorde, becauſe the Prophets propheſied in <hi>Baal,</hi> and went after thinges that did not profite, becauſe they had changed their glorie, euen their God which was their glorie, and who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8159:11"/>had made them glorious aboue all other people, and to bee ſhort, becauſe all eſtates were corrupt and out of courſe, the Prophet inferreth hereupon, <hi>O ye heauens, be aſtonied at this: hee afraide and vtterlie confounded, ſaith the Lord, Iere. 2.12.</hi> Hereby declaring, that the very inſenſible creatures of God did deteſt and abhorre the ſinne of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude &amp; vnkindnes, and as it were did trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at Gods moſt ſeuere and bitter iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt the ſame. The other was, that the heauens and earth (hearing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the Lord againſt his people) might iudge and determine between him &amp; them. So in the Prophet <hi>Micah, 6.2.</hi> the high hills and mountaines, the hard rocks, and mighty foundations of the earth are taken to witnes, and to decide betwixt him and his in this ſort. <hi>Heare ye (O mountains) the Lords quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and ye mightie foundations of the earth, for the Lord hath a quarrell againſt his people, and he will pleade with Iſraell.</hi> The ſumme whereof is this: that of the one part, the wickednes of the people was ſuch and ſo notorious, and of the other, the cauſe and quarrell of the Lorde ſo iuſt, that if the caſe were to be decided of the heauens &amp; earth, of the hills and mountaines, of the rocks &amp;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8159:12"/>mighty foundations of the earth, they wold ſtand all together on the Lords part againſt his people, they would giue ſentence with him againſt them, and (not without aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes) would iudge and condemne them of extreameſt madnes and impietie.</p>
            <p>But alas, that the heauens and earth, that the hills and mountaines, that the rocks and mightie foundations of the earth, that ſuch ſenſeles creatures ſhould condemne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde of ingratitude and vnkindnes? That they ſhould condemne <hi>Man,</hi> the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celent creature of God, indued with reaſon &amp; vnderſtanding? That the heauens ſhould be ſummoned to teſtifie againſt him, which are the Lords ſeate, and the earth to witnes againſt him, which is his footeſtoole. That dull and dumme creatures ſhould be more prompt and readie to follow and obey the Lords will, than they his people, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had giuen eyes to ſee, eares to heare, and an heart to perceiue. But ſo it is; they that ſhould haue liued beſt in order, are found to liue moſt out of courſe. For if the worlde be conſidered together with the partes and portions thereof in order and as they lie, we by ſearching ſhall ſee, and by ſeeing ſhal confeſſe euerie member thereof <hi>Man</hi> only
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8159:12"/>excepted) diligentlie and truely to doe his dutie. (Saith Dauid). <hi>The heauens declare the glorie of God, and the firmament ſheweth the workes of his hands. Pſa. 19.1.</hi> The Sun, Moone and Starres do keepe their courſes, the earth bringeth forth frute, the Sea paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not his appointed bounds, &amp; in all other things a ſingular dutie and obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their creatour, and yet they all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vnderſtanding: But <hi>Man</hi> for whoſe ſake all thinges were created, and whome God hath inriched with ſingular gifts, farre beyond any other of his creatures, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom he hath giuen the vſe of his word, <hi>a lanterne vnto his feete, and a light vnto his pathes; Pſa. 119.105.</hi> this <hi>Man</hi> will not be reclaimed; but walketh on ſtill in the ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſtoutnes of heart; that now the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is forced to appeale vnto deafe and dumme creatures, and ſaith; <hi>Heare, O Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and harken, O earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what? Doth the prophet make this exclamation and outcrie to the heauens &amp; earth of his own mind? Not ſo; for he ſaith, <hi>Quoniam Dominus locutus eſt, for the Lorde hath ſaide.</hi> As who ſhould ſay; I ſpeake not this of mine owne minde, I doe not this of mine owne authoritie, I came not before I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8159:13"/>was ſent, I vtter nothing of my ſelfe, but what the Lord did firſt reueale vnto me, &amp; which yee are bound to heare and hearken, beleeue, and obey; And therefore, <hi>Heare, O heauens, and hearken O earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It might haue ſeemed more methodically done, and fitter for manner and order of teaching, if the prophet ſtraight way vpon this his vehement exclamation and outcrie vnto the heauens and earth, had ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt, what they ſhould heare, than whome they ſhould heare. But it was more forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pearcing, yea and more requiſite too, that the prophet ſhuld firſt ſhew them whome they ſhould heare, than what they ſhould heare. VVhen Man doth ſpeake, the word is not ſo wel accepted &amp; receiued as when the Lorde doth ſpeake. The meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that is done from a Prince is more high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed, than that which cometh from a Subiect. VVhen the Prince ſpeketh, let the Subiect hold his peace; but when the Lord ſpeaketh, let all fleſh giue eare. <hi>The Lion hath roared (ſaith Amos) who will not bee a fraide? the Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but propheſie? Amos. 3.8.</hi> worthie is his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to bee reuerenced and obeyed of all his creatures which are in earth, whoſe voice
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8159:13"/>nothing, whether aboue or beneath, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen or in earth, ſenſible or inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ought to diſobey. <hi>Heare then, O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and hearken, O earth: for the Lord hath ſaide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which latter words, <hi>for the Lord hath ſaide</hi>) the Prophet commendeth vnto vs three ſpeciall points.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt the excellencie and worthines of the word of God, which <hi>Dauid</hi> preferreth <hi>before gold, before much fine gold; which hee counteth ſweeter than hony &amp; the hony comb, Pſal. 19.10.</hi> For it is that honye, whoſe ſweetnes doth both delight the ſoule, and alſo temper the troubles of this life, that they become tollerable and eaſie. It is that fire which burneth vp and conſumeth the figge leaues of vanitie, and wickedneſſe of mans hart whatſoeuer. It is that <hi>which drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as the rain, which ſtilleth as the dew, as the ſhower vpon the hearbes, and as the great raine vpon the graſſe. Deut. 2.2. It is the ſword of the ſpirit, Eph. 6.17. Sharper than any two edged ſword, entring through, euen to the deuiding a ſunder of the ſoule and the ſpirit, and of the ioyntes, and marowe. Heb. 4.12.</hi> It is that graine of muſtard ſeede <hi>Math. 13.31.</hi> which at the firſt is verie ſmall, but taking roote &amp;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8159:14"/>increaſing in the children of God, groweth to ſuch an height, that it reacheth the verie hart &amp; minde of man. It is that ſeed, whoſe rootes take ſuch deepe hold, &amp; are ſo firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie faſtned, that it neuer ceaſeth from grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till it bring the whole man into the quiet poſſeſſion of the kingdome of God. It is the forcible ſeede of regeneration, by which (through the working of the ſpirite of God) all muſt be regenerate and borne a new, as many as deſire to bee made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the eternall inheritance. It is that word of truth, by which God the father, the fountaine and welſpring of all goodnes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his free mercie, euen of his owne will begate vs, that we ſhould be as the firſt frutes of his creatures. <hi>Ia. 1.18.</hi> So wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Saint Peter</hi> in his 1. Epiſtle 1. Chapter &amp; verſe 23. <hi>Borne a new, not of mortall ſeed, but of immortall, by the word of God, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for euer.</hi> If I might ſtand vpon this point, I could bring many moſt excellent places of Scripture for the worthines here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and for the great benefits which <hi>Salomon</hi> deſcribeth, and which <hi>Dauid</hi> confeſſeth to haue receiued by the ſame, as namely, that hee had periſhed in the multitude of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, if the comforts thereof had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8159:14"/>his ſoule. <hi>Pro.</hi> 4. <hi>Pſa. 94.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondarilie, the prophet in theſe words <hi>(For the Lord hath ſaide)</hi> declareth in what eſtimation and reuerence his word is to bee had, &amp; the miniſters thereof: that his word is to be receiued, <hi>not as the word of men, but as it is indeede the word of God, which alſo worketh in them that beleeue; 1. Theſ. 2.13.</hi> &amp; that the Miniſters thereof are to bee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God: 1. Cor. 4.1.</hi> whome hee that contemneth, contemneth God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaide vnto the Iſralites; <hi>The Lord hath heard your murmurings which ye murmur againſt him: for what are we? Your murmurings are not againſt vs, but againſt the Lord. Ex. 16.8.</hi> Againe (concerning them) the Lord from his owne mouth ſaith vnto <hi>Samuell: they haue not caſt thee away, but they haue caſt mee awaie, that I ſhoulde not reigne ouer them. 1. Sa. 8.7.</hi> Our Sauiour to the Diſciples; <hi>he that heareth you heareth me, and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent mee. Lu. 10.16.</hi> And the Apoſtle vnto the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians, <hi>he that deſpiſeth vs, deſpiſeth not man but God, who hath ſent his holie ſpirite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs. 1. Theſ. 4.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:8159:15"/>3 Thirdly, out of theſe wordes <hi>(For the Lord hath ſaid)</hi> we learne; that the Prophets of God were wont, as often as they publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed any thing worthy admiration, whether it were to ſet forth Gods iuſtice, or to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his mercie) to ſay; <hi>This ſaith the Lord or the Lord hath ſpoken it;</hi> thereby decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that they vttred nothing of their own minde, but that which they had receiued from the mouth of the Lord. Which prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe was vſuall not only with the prophets, but alſo with Chriſt and his Apoſtles. For Chriſt ſaid vnto the Iewes: <hi>I doe nothing of my ſelfe, but as my Father hath taught me, ſo I ſpeake theſe things. Io. 8.28.</hi> Againe, <hi>I haue not ſpoken of my ſelfe; but the Father which ſent me, he gaue me a commandement what I ſhould ſaie, &amp; what I ſhould ſpeake. Io. 12.49. S. Iohn</hi> his Apoſtle likewiſe: <hi>That which we haue ſeene and hearde, declare wee vnto you. 1. Io. 1.3. S. Paul</hi> in like ſort: <hi>That which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto you, I receiued of the Lord. 1. Co. 11, 23,</hi> So in his Epiſtle to the Romanes (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating of the manner and order of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication) he putteth this queſton: <hi>for what ſaieth the ſcripture. Rom. 4.3.</hi> And in ſundry other places, when hee laboureth to proue what he had ſaide, he citeth the Scriptures;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8159:15"/>
               <hi>giuen by inſpiration of God,</hi> &amp; therefore <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to teach, to improue, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſnes, that the man of God, may bee perfect and prepared vnto euerie good worke. 2. Tim. 3.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhich diuine and heauenly practiſe of the Prophets, of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, would God the Papiſts of our daies: would once endeuour to imitate and followe. But they (ſtill like vnto their forefathers) plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with them in the bottomles pit of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, or rather giuen in the haughtines and mallice of hart to deceiue, preferre the <hi>Popes</hi> holines before the Scriptures: and the Scriptures which our Sauiour Chriſt vſed and confirmed with ſo manie miracles, and at laſt ſealed vpp with the effuſion of his precious blood; which came by inſpiration of God; <hi>2. Tim. 3.19.</hi> which the Prophets, Apoſtles, &amp; Fathers (as often as was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) alleged for teſtimonie and proofe theſe men haue vſed, and yet vſe to call a bare, dumme, vnprofitable, and deade Letter, They tell vs not what the Lorde hath ſaide, but what men haue ſaide, as Pardoners, Prieſts, Friers, and Popes them ſelues; as <hi>Alexander, Gregorie, Iohn, Clement,</hi> and others like.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8159:16"/>
            <p>They note vnto vs what Counſells haue decreed, what cuſtome hath confirmed, and what the <hi>Pope</hi> his vnlawfull ſoueraignetie hath eſtabliſhed; which ſeemeth to vs all one, as if he had ſaid, The Scriptures are to no purpoſe; or as good as nothing. Of which opinion was <hi>Cardinall Hoſius: who in his booke. De expreſſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbo Dei, Fol. 242. in lit. F.</hi> writeth thus: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anus eſt labor qui ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis impenditur.</hi> It is but loſt labour that is ſpent in the ſcriptures. <hi>Nos Dei de caelo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam potius expectabimus:</hi> VVee will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expect Gods pleaſure from heauen. <hi>Scriptura enim creatura eſt, &amp; egenum quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam elementum.</hi> For the Scripture is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and a certaine needy element. And in concluſion he pronounceth Sentence defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue in this wiſe: <hi>in Epilogo ad Sigiſmun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum regem Poloniae. Quod Eccleſia docet, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſum Dei verbum eſt: quod contra ſenſum, et conſenſum Eccleſiae docetur, expreſſum Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboli verbum eſt.</hi> That which the Church teacheth (by the Church I trow, meaning the Pope and his Cardinalls) is the expreſſe worde of God: what is taught againſt the meaning and conſent of the Church, is the expreſſe word of the Deuil. And long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him <hi>Guido (editus, An. 1495.)</hi> hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8159:16"/>which compiled that ſottiſh booke, <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus curatorum,</hi> (to iuſtifie the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; ſtuffe of Confirmation) putteth this downe for a Maxime &amp; infallable truth: <hi>In Tract. 3.1. Par. 2. de mat. confir. Licet non inueniatur in canonicis epiſtolis Diui Petri, tamen Dominus Papa habet in decretis Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae eccleſiae &amp;c.</hi> That though it bee not found in the canonicall Epiſtles of <hi>S. Peter;</hi> yet our Lord the <hi>Pope</hi> hath it in the decrees of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> &amp; this mounteth farre aboue and beyond all other authoritie whatſoeuer. Thus Chriſt muſt Surrender to <hi>Beliall;</hi> the Spouſe muſt giue place to <hi>Babilon:</hi> Truth to falſehood, and the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten worde to vnwritten verities: humane traditions muſt be hote and liuelie letters, and the ſcriptures, cold &amp; dead Elements; if wee hunger, our meate muſt bee chaffe in ſteed of wheate; and if we call for drinke, it muſt come from their broken and puddle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, full of mire and filth, <hi>Ier. 2.13.</hi> which neither haue nor are able to hold the water of power to refreſhe the withered ſoule of man: for the veines of the freſh and cleare ſpringing waters they haue ſtopped vp: that by this drift, the ſayings both of <hi>Ieremy</hi> and <hi>Eſaie,</hi> verified in the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as well pore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8159:17"/>as rich, haue beene brought on vs. <hi>The Elders of the Iewes</hi> (ſaith Ieremie) <hi>ſent their little ones to the wells, and they finding no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with ſhame and confuſion returned with their veſſels emptie. The poore and the needye</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſaie. 41.17.</hi>) <hi>ſought water, but no where found they any: their tongue was euen withered with thirſt.</hi> Euen ſo theſe men, by breaking in peeces the pipes and conduits, and by damming and choaking the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of liuing waters with dirte and mire, haue brought the people of God into a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull thirſt, and this was a miſery and a rufull ſtate: we haue felt it, let vs beware. We are counſelled, if we will follow counſell, and we are warned, if we will take warning, to beware of ſuch deceiuers, leaſt otherwiſe it come to paſſe, that as the <hi>Serpent beguiled Eue through his ſubtiltie, ſo our minds ſhould be corrupt from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt. 2. Cor. 11.3.</hi> If they bring with them <hi>Eſaies</hi> commiſſion and crie as he doth: <hi>Heare and hearken, for the Lord hath ſaid:</hi> Let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them as embaſſadours ſent vs from God, and let vs beleeue them. Otherwiſe, if they breed ſuſpition, let vs make proofe, as did thoſe noble men of <hi>Beroea,</hi> noble not ſo much for birth, as for courage in embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8159:17"/>the word of God with all readineſſe, and as they did, <hi>Act. 17.11.</hi> let vs ſearche thr ſcriptures daylie and diligentlye, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the thinges which they teach be ſo or not. And then if (vpon due trial &amp; proofe) wee finde that they bring vs counterfet coyne, that they come with the Reuelations of men which flow not from the mouth of the Lorde, what countenance ſoeuer they carry <hi>(where they Angells from heauen, that did vs the meſſage)</hi> by the commandement of <hi>Saint Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galathians, 1.8.</hi> let vs hold them accurſed.</p>
            <p>And yet there are that ſay, and will ſay; <hi>The Lord hath ſaid it,</hi> when the Lord neuer ſpake the worde. Such are the Prophets of Antichriſt, not vnlike vnto thoſe of Iſrael, which Propheſied after their own fantaſie, and ſaid; <hi>the Lord ſaith it, albeit the Lorde had not ſpoken. Eze. 13.7.</hi> But beholde, what the worde of the Lorde is againſt ſuch Prophets, which follow their owne ſpirite, and teach the people the counſailes of their own hearts. <hi>I am againſt them, mine hand ſhalbe vpon the Prophets that ſee vanitie, &amp; diuine lies: they ſhall not be in the aſſemblie of my people, neither ſhall they bee written in the writing of Iſrael, (Verſe. 8.9.)</hi> to wit, in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8159:18"/>booke of life in which the true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are written; <hi>neither ſhall they enter into the land of Iſraell: and that becauſe they haue deceiued my people ſaying peace;</hi> which <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie 6, 14.</hi> calleth <hi>a ſweet word,</hi> but it was not ſo, for there was no peace: &amp; <hi>one built vp a wall and others daubed it with vntempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red morter. Eze. 13.10.</hi> But ſaith the Lord, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er. 13.14. I will deſtroy the wall which they haue daubed with vntempered morter, and bring it downe to the ground, by a ſtormy wind which ſhall breake forth in my wrath, and by a greate ſhower in mine anger, and haileſtones in mine indignation, ſo that the foundation thereof ſhall be diſcouered, and it ſhall fall &amp; they ſhall be conſumed in the midſt therof, and ſhall know that I am the Lord.</hi> Thus will the Lorde accompliſh his wrath vpon the wall and vpon them that daubed it with vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter, euen with their own deuiſes, vnder the authoritie of Gods word. If then the Lord will thus deale with the wall, and with the daubers that daubed it with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered morter, let the builders take heed how they build the wall, and the daubers howe they daube it, leaſt the Lorde pull downe both wall and morter; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er 15.</hi> and they ſay, the wall is no more, neither the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8159:18"/>daubers thereof. And this much of the firſt part; namely, how <hi>Eſaie</hi> (by way of excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) hath inioyned (by the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God) the heauens to heare, and the earth to hearken, vnto the meſſage which hee is willed to doe vnto them from the mouth of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Nowe the Prophet goeth onward with the Lords moſt lamentable complaint con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ingratitude of his people, for whome he had done many and great good turnes. The complaint is this: <hi>I haue nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and brought vp children, but they haue rebelled againſt me.</hi> A moſt grieuous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, which conſiſteth of two partes. In the firſt, he expreſſeth his benefits beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon them. In the ſecond, hee decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth their ingratitude and rebellion againſt him. Hee expreſſeth his benefits towardes them in theſe wordes; <hi>I haue nouriſhed and brought vp children.</hi> He declareth their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude &amp; rebellion againſt him in theſe; <hi>but they haue rebelled againſt me.</hi> This their ingratitude and rebellion hee amplifieth in the verſe following by way of compariſon, or example of brute and dul beaſts. <hi>The Ox knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters Cribbe, but Iſrael hath not knowne: my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8159:19"/>hath not vnderſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue the ſumme of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint; by which almighty God, as a moſt vnhappie father, with lamentable voice doth deplore and bewaile the vnkindnes of his people, and withall doth recite what &amp; how great benifits hee had beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, but to no purpoſe. The complaint is verie ſhort if we marke the words, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie haynous and weightie if wee diligentlie weygh and examine the thing it ſelfe. For the Lord ſeemeth thus to ſay; Oh what an vnhappy father am I to haue ſuch vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children, whome I neither could, nor ought more to haue loued, than if they had come forth of mine owne loynes. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; he brought them out of the iron fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of Egipt, <hi>Deu. 4.20,</hi> where their liues were bitter vnto them by ſore labor in clay and bricke. <hi>Ex. 1.14.</hi> He went before them by day in a piller of a cloude to lead them the way; and by night in a piller of fire to giue them light, that they might goe both by day and by night. <hi>Exod. 13.21.</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided the red ſea in two parts, and made Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell to paſſe through the midſt of it, which when the Egyptians attempted to do, they were drowned, <hi>Exod. 14.21. Pſa. 136.13.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:8159:19"/>At their deſire he brought Quailes, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them with the bread of heauen; <hi>Pſ. 105.40.</hi> in ſo much that (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith.) Man did eate the bread of Angels. <hi>Pſal. 78.25.</hi> When they were thirſtie and had no water to drinke, <hi>Pſal. 105.41.</hi> he opened the rocke, and the waters flowed out, and ran in the drie places like a riuer. For their ſakes he ſmote diuers nations, <hi>Pſal. 135.10.</hi> and ſlew mightie kings, <hi>Pſal. 136.19.</hi> as <hi>Sihon</hi> king of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> &amp; <hi>Og</hi> king of <hi>Baſan,</hi> and all the kingdomes of <hi>Canaan, Num. 21.33.</hi> and gaue their land to be an heritage, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen an heritage vnto <hi>Iſrael</hi> his people. He made them a mightie nation, a fearfull, and a terrible to all the princes and potentates of the earth, <hi>Deut. 32.10.</hi> He found them in the land of the wilderneſſe, in a waſte, &amp; roaring wilderneſſe: he led them about, he taught them, and kept them as the apple of his eye. As an Eagle ſtirreth vp her neſt, fluttereth ouer her birdes, ſtretcheth out her winges, taketh them, and beareth them on her wings; So the Lord alone led them, and caried them vp to the high places of the earth, that they might eate the fruits of the fields, and ſuck honie out of the ſtone, and oile out of the harde rock; Butter of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8159:20"/>kine, and milke of ſheepe, with fat of the Lambes, and Rams fed in <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and goats, with the fat of the graines of wheate, and drinke the licour of the red grape. So in the ſecond of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> the Lorde ringeth in the eares of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the ſumme of his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits in this ſort; <hi>Iere. 2.2.</hi> I remember thee, with the kindeneſſe of thy youth; and the Ioue of thy marriage, when thou wenteſt after me in the wilderneſſe, in a land that was not ſowne. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a thing halowed vnto the Lord, and his firſt fruites, choſen aboue all other to ſerue the Lorde onely, and the firſt offered to the Lord of all other nations. And by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> (amongſt other his benefites towarde <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>) thus ſaith the Lorde: <hi>Ezech. 16.6. When thou waſt polluted in thy owne bloud:</hi> to wit, when thou waſt in thy filthineſſe and forſaken of all men, <hi>I tooke thee and gaue thee life, for</hi> I <hi>ſaide vnto thee, thou ſhalt liue. I cauſed thee to multiplie as the budde of the fielde, and thou hast increaſed and waxen great, and thou hast gotten excellent orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: thy breaſts are faſhioned, thine haire is growne.</hi> verſe. 11. <hi>I decked thee vvith ornaments, and I put bracelets vppon thine handes, and a chaine on thy necke. I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8159:20"/>put a frontlet vppon thy face, and earings in thine eares, and a beautifull crowne vppon thine head. Thus waſt thou deckt vvith golde and ſiluer, and thy raym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt was of fine linnen, and ſilke, and broidered worke: thou diddeſt eate fine flowre, and Honie: and Oile, and thou vvast verie beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and thou diddest growe vp into a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> And to bee ſhorte; what benefite was there, which the Lorde beſtowed not vppon his people? What could hee haue doone more vnto his Vineyarde, <hi>Eſay. 5.4.</hi> which he did not doe vnto it? <hi>He planted it in a very fruitfull hill, he hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, and gathered out the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones of it; he planted it with the best plantes, hee built a tower in the middeſt thereof, and made a wine preſſe therein.</hi> This did the Lorde for his Vineyard.</p>
            <p>Surelye the Vineyarde of the Lorde of hoaſts, was the houſe of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> were his pleaſant plante. <hi>verſe. 4.</hi> Then the Lorde looked that his Vineyarde ſhoulde bring foorth ſweete Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pes, but it brought foorth wilde and ſowre grapes: hee looked for iudgement, but beholde oppreſſion, <hi>verſe. 7.</hi> for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, but beholde a dolefull crying:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8159:21"/>for obedience, but behold a rebellion. <hi>I haue nouriſhed &amp; brought vp chillldren</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but they haue rebelled againſt me.</hi> I haue nouriſhed and brought them vp; I haue done the duty of a father, I haue performed what was required of my part; I haue caried them out of all danger, I haue made them the lot and portion of mine inheritance, I haue fed them with the beſt and cheefeſt things of the earth, I haue beſtowed many and infinite good turnes vpon them (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expreſſed) and yet ſee: this is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence which they yeeld vnto me for all that I haue done; <hi>They haue rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may ſeeme that the Lord doth not iuſtly charge his people with ingratitude and diſobedience; for they offered many ſacrifices: <hi>Eſa. 1.11.</hi> they offered the burnt offrings of rammes, the fat of fed beaſts, the bloud of bullocks, of Lambes, and of goats; They did what the law could require. They obſerued the new moones, <hi>verſ. 13.</hi> Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths and ſolemne dayes. They had their aſſemblies, and appointed feaſts: they ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out their hands, and made many prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And yet for all theſe (which they did, or could do) they are counted a ſinfull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8159:21"/>a people laden with iniquitie, a ſeed of the wicked, corrupt children, which had forſaken the Lord, &amp; prouoked <hi>the holy one of Iſrael</hi> to anger; <hi>ver. 4.</hi> and in ſuch ſort, as that he hated &amp; abhord their feaſt daies, &amp; would not ſmel in their ſolemne aſſemblies, <hi>Amo. 5.21.</hi> nor accept their burnt offrings, meate offrings, nor regarde the peace offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of their fat beaſts: and all was, becauſe they did theſe and ſuch like without faith and mercie, euen in the full meaſure of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and diſſimulation.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Vzziah</hi> himſelf, called alſo <hi>Azariah</hi> 2. <hi>Kin. 15.1</hi> (in whoſe time this our prophet bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to propheſie) after that God had bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him maruellouſly, &amp; had giuen him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notable victories, &amp; thereby was grown to be ſtrong, lifted vp his heart, and vſurped the prieſts office, and went into the temple of the Lord to burne incenſe vpon the altar of incenſe, and when he was willed to leaue off, would not, but waxed wroth, as it is in the ſecond of <hi>Chronicles</hi> and <hi>26.</hi> chap. v. <hi>19. Ieruſalem</hi> a faithfull citie, and which had promiſed fidelitie vnto God, as a wife to her husband, is now become a common harlot, and a filthie ſtrumpet, <hi>Eſa. 1.21.</hi> She was once full of iudgement, and iuſtice was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8159:22"/>lodged within her breſt: but now ſhe is full of rauen, crueltie and deceit. <hi>verſe. 22.</hi> Her ſiluer is become droſſe, and her wine is mixt with water. The teſtimonies of the Lord which ſometime were pure and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out droſſe, like vnto ſiluer that is tried with fire, are now defiled with phariſaicall tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and doctrines of men. The comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Lord which were like vnto pure wine reioycing the heart, through watery dregs, haue loſt their ſtrength, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and beautie, <hi>verſe. 23.</hi> The princes of the people were rebellious and compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theeues: they loued giftes, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after rewardes, they iudged not the fatherleſſe, neither did the widowes cauſe come before them. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2.8. The Prieſts ſaid not ſo much as, <hi>where is the Lorde?</hi> and they that ſhould miniſter the lawe, <hi>knew not God. Deut. 32.15.</hi> He that ſhould haue beene vpright, when he waxed fatte, and groſe, and was laden with fatneſſe, ſpurned with his heele, and forſooke the Lorde that made him, &amp; regarded not the ſtrong God of his ſaluation. And therefore the ſtate and condition of <hi>Iudah</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> being thus corrupt, whom neither the benefits of God could win, nor his puniſhments amend, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8159:22"/>Lord by his Prophet, dooth iuſtly charge them with ingratitude and diſobedience in this ſort: <hi>They haue rebelled againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein they did rightly imitate and follow their forefathers, <hi>Pſal. 78.8.</hi> a ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne and rebellious generation: a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whoſe heart was not aright, and whoſe ſpirit was not faithfull vnto God. For no ſooner had God brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of <hi>Egipt,</hi> out of the houſe of bondage, with a mighty hand and ſtretched out arme, <hi>Pſal. 106.7.</hi> but they forgate his great goodneſſe, and rebelled at the Sea, euen at the red Sea. <hi>Exo. 16.3.</hi> In the wilderneſſe of <hi>Sin</hi> they grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for bread and fleſh, <hi>Exod. 17.2.</hi> and in <hi>Rephidim</hi> for water. They made a calfe in <hi>Horeb, Exod. 32.4.</hi> &amp; worſhipped the mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten image. <hi>Pſa. 106.19.</hi> They maliced <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron,</hi> the holy one of the Lord. <hi>v. 16.</hi> They would haue ſtoned <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua. Nom. 14.10.</hi> They ioined themſelues vnto <hi>Baal peor,</hi> &amp; did eat the offrings of the dead <hi>Pſa. 106.28.</hi> They ſacrificed their ſonnes and daughters vnto deuils, &amp; ſhed innocent bloud, euen the bloud of their ſonnes and daughters, whom they offred vnto the idols of <hi>Canaan; Deut. 32.17.</hi> gods whom they knew not, new gods that came newly vp, &amp;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8159:23"/>forſooke the Lorde God of their fathers, which brought them out of the land of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,</hi> and followed other gods, as <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> the gods of the people that were round about them, and bowed vnto them. Wherefore the wrath of the Lord was hote againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he deliuered them into the hands of ſpoilers that ſpoiled them, and ſolde them into the hands of their enemies round about them. Notwithſtanding, the Lord raiſed vp Iudges, which deliuered them out of the hands of their oppreſſours, <hi>ve. 16.</hi> but they would not obey their Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for they wet a whoring after other gods and worſhipped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Iudg. 10.6.</hi> as the gods of <hi>Aram, Zidon,</hi> and <hi>Moab,</hi> the gods of the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> &amp; forſooke the Lorde God, and ſerued not him. And thus they rebelled and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie to the dayes of <hi>Iohn the fore-runner,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> inſomuch that of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; (before him) of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> they are called, <hi>Progenies viperarum,</hi> the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of vipers <hi>Mat. 3.7.</hi> And becauſe they were the children of them which mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thred the prophets, &amp; fulfilled the meaſure of their fathers <hi>Mat. 23.31,</hi> the lord vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth &amp; caſteth in their teeth not onely their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8159:23"/>owne, but alſo their fathers malice. Many a time would the Lord haue gathered them together, <hi>Matt. 23 37.</hi> as the hen doth her chickens vnder her wings, but they would not: And therefore did <hi>Stephan</hi> to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces charge them with ſtubborneſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, calling them <hi>Act. 7.51. ſtifnecked and of vncircumciſed hearts, and eares al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reſiſting the holy Ghoſt, as their fathers did.</hi> So that, though <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> after a ſort, could colour their rebellion and ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart againſt the Lord, and againſt his annointed, with the multitude of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, <hi>Eſa. 1.11.</hi> with the burnt offerings of Rams, and fat of fed beaſts, with the bloud of bullockes, of Lambes, and of goates, with the obſeruation of new moones, Sabbaths, and ſolemne daies: with the ſtretching out of hands, and making many praiers: yet, we ſee what they are, and the Lord (who alone looketh into the harts of all) by the prophet here chargeth the very <hi>Rulers</hi> to be rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious &amp; companions of theeues: <hi>ve. 23,</hi> yea, and the whole packe of them (for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie and wickedneſſe) to be like vnto the princes of <hi>Sodoma</hi> and people of <hi>Gomorah.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The application.</head>
               <p>And now (to applie theſe former points
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8159:24"/>vnto our ſelues, before we come to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggeration of this peoples ingratitude and vnkindneſſe) let vs take ſome ſhort view, whether our condition be the ſame with the condition of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ours be better than theirs was.</p>
               <p>The Lorde our God (as yee all know) hath nouriſhed and brought vp vs his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in as good and ample manner as euer he did the <hi>Iewes</hi> his elect and choſen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. He hath giuen vs for our comfort, <hi>Pſa. 8.7.8.</hi> the beaſts of the field, the foules of the ayre, and the fiſhes of the ſea. He brought vs out of the yron fornace of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Egipt,</hi> at what time the <hi>Egyptian</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants made vs wearie of our liues, with ſore labourin the clay and bricke of helliſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and with all maner of bondage, which they laide vpon vs moſt cruelly. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, the Lorde hath gone before vs by day, in a pillar of a cloude, and by night in a pillar of fire, to lead vs the way, and to giue vs light, that we might go both by day and by night, out of all danger. He hath giuen vs <hi>Manna</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen: not <hi>Manna,</hi> of which the Fathers did eate in the wilderneſſe, and are dead; but a liuing <hi>Manna,</hi> a <hi>Manna</hi> that giueth life vnto the world; a <hi>Manna,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8159:24"/>of which he that truly eateth, ſhall liue for euer. <hi>Ioh. 6 38.</hi> The Iſraelites (after they had drunke of the water out of the rocke) thirſted againe: but of the water, which he ſhall giue vs, if we once drinke, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be more a thirſt; <hi>Joh 4.14.</hi> for it is the water of life, euen the grace and loue of God in his ſonne Chriſt, ſhed abroad in our hearts, by the holy Ghoſt, vnto eternall life. This our God (for our peace) hath ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of late yeares <hi>Sihon</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and <hi>Og</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who ſought to make the Lords he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage an abhomination: that ſo (to this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day) the heritage ſtandeth as it did, it is as it was, and in as good plight, if not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; it remaineth in the hand of the right owner, &amp; we truſt that it ſhall ſtill remaine, euen in the hand and poſſeſſion of <hi>Iſrael</hi> his ſeruant; for which we do, and ſhall praiſe his holy &amp; bleſſed name for euer. This our God the lord God of hoſts, hath made vs a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nation, a fearefull, and a terrible to all the Princes &amp; Potentates of the earth. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducteth vs, not by <hi>Ioſua,</hi> but by a <hi>Ieſus:</hi> not to a terreſtrial, but to a celeſtial <hi>Canaan,</hi> the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of eternall felicitie, whoſe brightneſſe is God, whoſe light is the lambe: the lot of the faithfull, and the poſſeſſion of the ſaued.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8159:25"/>The Lord finding vs in this vale of miſerie (as he found <hi>Iaacob</hi> in the land of a roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wilderneſſe, <hi>Deuteronomie 23.9.10.</hi>) hath ledde vs by his ſpirite, taught vs by his worde, gouerned vs by his grace, and kept vs as the Apple of his eye. As the Eagle, he ſtirreth vp his neſt, he fluttereth ouer vs his young ones, ſtretcheth out the winges of his mercie, taketh and beareth vs on the ſame to the beſt and ſureſt places of the earth: that ſo we eate the fruites of the fields, and ſucke honie, not from the ſtone, as did the Iewes, but from the Bee: and oile not from the rocke (as they) but from the Oliue: we eate the butter of kine, and the milke of ſheepe, with the fat of Lambes and Rams; fed, not in <hi>Baſhan,</hi> but in <hi>England,</hi> with the fat of the graines of wheate, and for good and perfect digeſtion, we drawe from the enemy the licour of the red grape. This our good and gratious God hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs to multiply as the bud of the field. We are (to the knowledge of the nations round about vs) increaſed and waxen great: many of vs haue gotten many goodly and excellent ornaments. Our breaſts are faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, our haire is growne. The Lorde hath giuen vs riche and precious iewels: brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8159:25"/>for our hands, chaines for our necks, frontlets for our faces, earings for our eares, beautifull things for our heads; in which, would God we did not delight and reioyce ſo much as we do. The Lord hath decked vs with gold and ſiluer: our raiment is of the fineſt linnen, and ſilke, and broidered worke: we eate fine floure, and honie, and oile: yea, better things than euer did the <hi>Iewes;</hi> and thus wee become beautifull, more than the ſonnes and daughters of <hi>Zion;</hi> and we are growne into a kingdom, God graunt not into pride. The <hi>Iewes</hi> in the firſt of <hi>Haggei, verſ. 8.</hi> are commanded to go vp to the hill <hi>Lebanon,</hi> which was not within the borders of <hi>Iewry,</hi> but of <hi>Zidon</hi> &amp; <hi>Tyrus, Ezra. 3.7.</hi> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence to bring home Cedarwood for the building of the Temple. Truly a figure of the Lordes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant mercie, and moſt comfortable for vs Gentiles; that albeit wee bee not borne of <hi>Iewes:</hi> yet we are trees meete to builde Gods houſe with, and God willeth vs to bee brought home vnto him by the preaching of his worde, that wee may be plankes or boardes, baſes or props, ſides or poſtes, pillars or beames, rafters or tenons, one thing or other of that houſe, wherein
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8159:26"/>himſelfe will dwell, and he delighted with vs, and among whome he will declare his glorie.</p>
               <p>Beſide all theſe (which hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie obſerued for a bleſſing vpon Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and Iudah) <hi>Eſa. 5.1.2.</hi> the Lord hath planted his vineyard in a very frutful ſoile; he hath giuen it a skilfull vinitor, one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with all gifts and qualities neceſſarie for regiment; euen a learned, religious, gentle, mercifull, gracious and louing Prince, by name <hi>Elizabeth, the reſt of God, the ſeauenth of God, and fulnes of the othe of God:</hi> a great bleſſing, the Lorde conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue it, and make vs thankfull for it.</p>
               <p>This skilfull vinitor <hi>(our gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne)</hi> comparable for fortitude with <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua,</hi> for magnanimitie with <hi>Gedeon,</hi> for victories with <hi>Macchabeus,</hi> for wiſedome with <hi>Salomon,</hi> for zeale with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> for deutoion with <hi>Dauid;</hi> hath cauſed the ſtones that peſtered the vineyard to bee gathered out; the briers and thornes to be grubbed vp; rubbidge and whatſoeuer was noyſome to be remooued; <hi>2. Theſ. 2.3. Antichriſt</hi> the man of ſin with his traſh and traditions, to bee exiled: that nowe the fielde is cleared, the vineyard clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8159:26"/>the Church purged, and all this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and more, without any great ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or tumult at all. It was the Lordes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it is wonderfull in the eyes of as manie as doe truely behold it. No viney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, no Church, no people vnder the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens more inriched with the bleſſings of God: ſo that the Lord may iuſtly ſay vnto vs, as he did vnto his people of old, <hi>Eſ. 4.5.</hi> what more could I haue done vnto my vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyard which I haue not done vnto it? The Lord haue the glorie for it: and he in his mercie, preſerue, keepe and maintaine the vinitor our gracious queene, in health, wealth, peace and proſperitie, that (to the ioy and comfort of all her loyall, heartie true &amp; truſtie ſubiects) ſhe may long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, liue and reigne <hi>an old mother in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> &amp; he that from the verie bottome of his heart doth not ſo wiſh and praie, and ſay Amen, <hi>the rauens of the valley pick out his eyes, and the young Eagles eate them vp. Pro. 30.17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This vineyard ſo planted in a moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ground, cleanſed from ſtone, thorne, &amp; brier, watered with the dew of Gods truth, cheriſhed with his Sacramentes, pruned with the two edged ſword of his moſt holy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8159:27"/>ſpirit, vnder propped with the authoritie of zealous magiſtrates, fortified with good and godly lawes, to keepe both roote and braunche in order; hath brought foorth many a goodly and pleaſaunt grape: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, peace ſpirituall and peace ciuill: peace toward God, peace amongſt men, and amongſt our ſelues; and ſo the peace of conſcience, which paſſeth all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vnderſtanding: pleaſant grapes, and a riche bleſſing. He that hath felt the euill of warre, can beſt ſpeake of the good of peace. Warre, as a Locuſt, maketh ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie; but peace, like vnto the morning and euening dew, worketh plenty, as <hi>Eraſ. Apo. lib.</hi> 6. noteth; <hi>Croeſus</hi> king of <hi>Lydia</hi> by this onely argument preferred peace before warre; <hi>Quòd pacis tempore filii ſepelirent patres, in bello contrà patres ſepelirent libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros;</hi> that in the time of peace, children did burie their fathers; contrariwiſe in warre, fathers did burie their children. So contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is the fruite of warre to the fruite of peace; which we (through the benefit of God vnder his <hi>Anointed</hi>) haue enioyed long time without any effuſion of bloud to ſpeake of, except of a ſort of <hi>Archtraitors,</hi> who receiued but the rewarde they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8159:27"/>and which I pray God all traitours with their adherents may receiue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, if they practiſe, conſpire, and rebell as they did.</p>
               <p>This floriſhing peace hath made not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this <hi>Citie,</hi> but alſo the whole lande to flowe, like another <hi>Canaan,</hi> with milke and honie. The God of peace hath done this for vs; he be praiſed therefore, and proſper her maieſtie, by whom it is gouerned and maintained.</p>
               <p>Whereas the <hi>Nations</hi> about vs ſtruggle in the field, tumble in warre, and wallow in bloud, expecting no end of their miſeries, but vtter ruine and deſolation; we in the meane while ſit at home by our fires in our furred gownes, corked ſlippers, trimmed buskins, and warme mittons. <hi>Am. 4.6. We lie vpon our coſtly beds, and ſtretch out our ſelues vpon them; we eate the Lambes of the flocke, and the Calues out of the ſtall.</hi> verſe. <hi>5. We ſing to the ſound of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ioll, the Harpe and Pipe, and wine are in our feaſts, and the wine we drinke in bowles: Eſa. 5.12. Am. 6.6.</hi> In which great peace and plentifulneſſe, God make vs worthily to conſider the workes of his handes, and to be ſory for the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his bretheren,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8159:28"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. 6.</hi> of which now many are ſlaine in <hi>Fraunce, Flanders,</hi> and els wheare, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Goſpel, propagation of the truth, and ſafetie of this Land. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer (whereas the nations &amp; people about vs do eate in feare, and drinke in dread, and like fearefull hares doe flee awaye at the wagging of euerie leafe) we ſit quiet and ſafe, as did <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudab, 1. King. 4.20.</hi> like vnto the ſand of the Sea in number, eating, drinking &amp; making me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; euery man vnder his vine, and vnder his Boothe, from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beer-ſheba;</hi> to wit, from the one end of this land to the other. For God hath made the bars of the gates of our <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſtrong, <hi>Pſa. 147.5.</hi> and hath bleſſed our children within hir. He hath ſet peace in hir borders, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied hir poore with the floure of wheate. His worde is come from <hi>Iaacob,</hi> and his ſtatutes from <hi>Iſrael</hi> vnto vs; the beſt and greateſt bleſſing that may be. <hi>He hath not dealt thus with euerie Nation, verſ. 20.</hi> as hee hath dealt with vs, the leaſt Nation of all: Our puniſhment and fall will bee the greater, if we be not thankefull. It muſt be confeſſed that ſome ſtonnes haue bin rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in hir <hi>Maiesties</hi> daies; &amp; before time
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8159:28"/>in the daies of hir deare brother <hi>King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſixt,</hi> which ſomwhat diſturbed our happy reſt. But the Prince of peace, &amp; ſoueraigne Lord of our tranquillitie, ſoone ceaſed the waues of the ſea, ſtilled the fury &amp; madnes of thoſe heathen, miraculouſly preuented their wicked deuiſes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the deuiſers of them. Thus was the Lorde of Hoaſts iealous for his <hi>Zion,</hi> with great iealouzie, <hi>he was iealous for hir with great wrath, Zach. 8.2.</hi> Hee was not vnmindfull of his people, nor forgetfull of his inheritance. A mother may forget hir childe, and take no compaſſion on the ſon of hir wombe; <hi>Eſay, 49.15.</hi> ſuch ſtepmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there are. But though ſuch (vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally giuen) forget, yet will not the Lord forget <hi>Zion:</hi> for he hath grauen hir vppon the palme of his hands, and hir walls are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in his ſight. <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſhipmaſter (our ſaluation) <hi>Matth 8.24.</hi> ſlept in the ſhipp on a pillow, the ſhip couered with waues: the <hi>Diſciples, Mar. 4.38.</hi> with no litle dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and diſtruſt awoke him, they put him out of his napp: A faithles and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les labour. For hee that keepeth <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhall neither ſlumber nor ſleepe: <hi>Pſal. 121 4.</hi> wee haue felt the experiment. For the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8159:29"/>Lorde in our Cities diſtreſſe, in the time of <hi>Commotion,</hi> (as we call it) or inſurrection, awaked as <hi>one out of ſleepe, and as a Giant refreſhed with wine. Pſal. 78.65. He ſmote his enemies and ours in the hinder parts, and put them to a perpetuall ſhame,</hi> verſe, 66. <hi>They ran about vs like Bees; but they were extinct ſodainly as a fire of thornes.</hi> Pſal. 12. <hi>Our ſoule eſcaped, euen as a bird out of the ſnare of the fowler; the ſnare was broken, and we deliuered,</hi> Pſal. 124.7. <hi>The Plowers would haue plowed vpon our backs, and made long furrowes at their pleaſure,</hi> Pſal. 129.3. <hi>But the righteous Lord tooke in hand the two edged ſword of his iustice, and hewed the ſnares and cordes of thoſe wicked in pieces: (verſ. 4.5.)</hi> He in like meaſure reward as many as haue euill will at Sion. <hi>This was the Lords worke, and it is maruellous in our eies.</hi> Pſal. 118.23. <hi>This is the day which the Lord made. we will reioice and bee glad in it,</hi> verſe, 24. This is the day which you call <hi>Ieſus daie,</hi> whether becauſe it is ſo fixed in the Calender I knowe not; but ſure I am, that it was <hi>Ieſus</hi> day vnto you, a day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. For if <hi>Ieſus</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> had not been on our ſide, <hi>Pſal. 114.1.</hi> (may not <hi>Iſraal,</hi> but <hi>Exeter</hi> now ſay) if the Lorde had not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8159:29"/>bin on our ſide, when men roſe vp againſt vs, they had ſwallowed vs vp quicke (ſo vnable wer we to reſiſt) when their wrath was kindled againſt vs. The waters had drowned vs, the ſtreame and ſwelling wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had gone ouer our ſoule, verſe, 4. But praiſed be the Lord, who gaue vs not ouer for a pray vnto their teeth.</p>
               <p>And thus hath our good &amp; gratious God continued his fauor toward vs to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, that there is no leading into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, nor any complaining in our ſtreets. Pſal. 144.14. Bleſſed are wee that bee in ſuch a caſe: yea bleſſed are we which haue the Lorde for our God. For this great calme, for this miraculous peace, let vs thanke the Lord.</p>
               <p>But what? are we thankefull vnto him for theſe and other his bleſſinges? or liue we as children obedient to a father? If we do not, would we did; all doo not. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, how many of vs (like vnto <hi>Iſrael</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudah</hi>) are turned backe, and ſtarted aſide like a broken bowe? <hi>Pſal. 78.57.</hi> The Lorde looketh that we ſhould bring forth ſweete grapes, but wee bring forth ſowre ones. There are at this very day in our ſtreets, vſury, deceit, crueltie, and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8159:30"/>Wee haue (as the Iewes had) our Sabbaths and ſolemne dayes, our aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and appointed feaſts; we ſtretch out our hands and make manie praiers as they did: and yet ſee (as theirs were) our harts (if not our hands) are full of blood. <hi>Eſa. 1.13.15.</hi> Nowe that wee are waxen fatte and groſe; nowe that wee haue what wee would haue (as did Iſrael) we ſpurne with the heele, we forſake the Lord that made vs, and regard not the mightie and ſtrong God of our ſaluation. <hi>Deu. 32.15.</hi> We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to loath <hi>Manna,</hi> and to long for the fleſh pots of Egipt. <hi>Num. 11.6.</hi> Wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that wee know God; but our workes teſtifie, that we denie him. <hi>Exo. 19.3.</hi> As for the word of the Lorde, wee count it vaine: <hi>Tit. 1.19.</hi> we can be content to ſay to the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers,</hi> ſee not, and to the Prophets, propheſie errours. <hi>Eſa. 36.10.</hi> Like vnto the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Anathoth</hi> we deſire to bee flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and ſoothed in our ſins. <hi>Ier, 11.17.</hi> The Lord hath ſet watchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vs that crie take heed of the ſound of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; but we ſay, we will not take heed. <hi>Ier. 6.17.</hi> He hath commanded vs to aſke for the old waie, which is the good way; the waie wherein the patriarks and prophets
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8159:30"/>haue walked, directed by the worde of God: <hi>ver. 16.</hi> but we ſay we wil not walke therein; we will go rather the broad way that leadeth to deſtruction. <hi>Mat. 7.13.</hi> we drinke iniquitie like water: wee haue as great a deſire to ſin, as they that are thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie haue a deſire to drinke. <hi>Iob. 15.16.</hi> We draw wickednes vnto vs with cordes, and ſin (as it were) with cart ropes; <hi>Eſa. 5.18.</hi> wee vſe all the allurements and prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that canbe, to freeſe together the conſcience in ſin and impietie. And yet we can ſpeake of truth and of veritie, of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercie, of the knowledge of God and his lawes, and of ſundrie other high points: but when we are brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ballance, we are found too light, &amp; when we are drawen vnto the touchſtone for trial, we proue droſſe. For what do the Sunnes of men find in our ſhops &amp; ſhop-houſes, in our wares and ware-houſes, but fraud and deceit, if not worſe? Truely ſaid <hi>Tertullian, Lib. de patientia, pag. 13. ſect. 7 Lata atque diffuſa eſt operatio mali.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The operation, or handicrafte of miſchiefe is wide and diffuſed all abroad; more nowe than euer it was.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8159:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Apostle</hi> left written many yeares paſt, that the <hi>vvhole vvorld lieth in vvickednes:</hi> Firſt <hi>Iohn, 5.</hi> Chapter and <hi>19.</hi> verſe, which if it lay buried in wickednes then, how may wee thinke it to lie buried in wickedneſſe, now being old, bowing and winding it ſelfe euen for age to the pit of deſtruction?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> muſt bee iuſt, and his <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> commeth homeward to our dores, and the Lorde as then with the inhabitants in Iſraell, ſo nowe with vs <hi>in England,</hi> hath a controuerſie, becauſe in <hi>Hoſ. 4.1.2.</hi> there is <hi>no truth, nor mercie, nor knovvledge of God in the land; but ſvvearing, and lying, &amp; killing, and ſtealing, and vvhoring, they break out, and blood toucheth blood;</hi> miſchiefe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon miſchiefe, one ſtill falling on the neck of another; and all theſe with many moe committed without any dreade, or feare of God at all. For ſo man dooth not ſee vs, we paſſe not; fearing more the face of man, than the wrath of God; inſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance the very ſonnes of <hi>Ammon,</hi> who coueting to force his ſiſter <hi>Tamar, 2. Sam. 13.</hi> cauſed euery man to go out from him, as aſhamed to worke that villanie before men, which hee feared not to commit in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8159:31"/>the ſight of his God. This <hi>Ammon</hi> (wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Ammon</hi>) hath left <hi>Ammons</hi> in great ſtore behinde him, as much forgetfull of God and his lawes as euer himſelfe was, if not more. For as he feared, ſo do we the eyes of men: and thus, and thus, we think in our hearts, <hi>Eccle. 23.18.</hi> Who ſeeth vs? wee are compaſſed about with darkenes; the walls couer vs; no body marketh vs; whome neede wee to feare? the <hi>moſt High</hi> will not remember our ſinnes; albeit hee remembreth them well inough, and ſtill looketh downe vppon them from his <hi>holie Mountaine,</hi> and beholdeth them in the moſt ſecret parts; <hi>his eies beeing ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times brighter than the ſunne beames, beholding all the vvaies of men, and the ground of the deepe.</hi> And therefore ſuch i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations of the thoughts of mens hearts ſhall periſh, and they in them: ſuch ſhifts and turning of deuiſes ſhall be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as the Potters clay, <hi>Eſay, 29.16.</hi> For (notwithſtanding all their craft) they ſhal bee able to eſcape the Lordes wrath no more than the clay that is in the Potters hand of power to deliuer itſelf. But ſo long as men will dwell in this minde and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he that planted the eare doth not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8159:32"/>heare, and that hee that formed the eye, doth not ſee; what merueile is it, if they giue themſelues vnto wantonnes, to work all vncleannes, euen with greedines? <hi>Eph. 4.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is another ſort of vs, who thogh we perceiue and will confeſſe that there is nothing ſo hid which God ſeeth not; that hee knoweth our downe ſitting and our vpriſing, <hi>Pſa. 159.2.3.4.</hi> that he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth all our thoughtes long before, that he is about our pathes and about our beddes, and ſpieth out all our waies, that there is not a worde in our tongues, which he knoweth not altogether: yet wee reſt perſwaded that God hath feete of woll, and will puniſh ſlowly, or neuer. As for the deſerued tokens of his wrath, nowe hanging ouer our heades, and readie to be powred vpon vs, for our manifold ſinnes and damnable iniquities, what of them? We count them as buggs; bugges to fray children. The Lorde our God hath gone by vs <hi>in a mightie ſtrong winde: but we ſay the Lord was not in the winde. After the minde came an earthquake: but wee ſay the Lord was not in the Earthquake. After the Earthquake came fire: but we ſay, the Lorde
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8159:32"/>was not in the fire. After the fire came a ſtill and ſoft voice: and yet wee will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If God withdraw his heauy hand for a time, to trie if we wil amend with a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle correction before hee lay on vs a ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: we fall to our old faſhions, we forget God, his rodde, our dutie, and his reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, attributing his plagues to vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable weather, peſtilent aires, or to ſome vnhappie chaunce, as though they were not ſent of God to nurture vs rightly in the dutie and obedience of Children to a father.</p>
               <p>So in the daies of moſt cruell Poperie and bloodie perſecution, wee cried; <hi>O Lord our God, deliuer vp this once, and wee will euer take heede hereafter howe wee fall to Apostaſie and offende thy diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But nowe beeing deliuered, wee are worſe; more vnthankefull and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent than euer before; which apparant wickedneſſe, ſurely the righteous God in his due time, will not ſuffer to eſcape without ſome manifeſt token of his high indignation and moſt heauie diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:8159:33"/>
               <p>When Prince <hi>Edvvard the ſixt,</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away for our vnthankefulnes, there enſued <hi>Mariana tempora,</hi> Lamentable times: and then too, this was the wiſh of many one, bounded with a vowe: O that the <hi>Maſſe Booke</hi> were burnt, &amp; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion booke reſtored againe. O that theſe <hi>mitred Biſhops</hi> were ſent packing, &amp; <hi>zealous Pastors</hi> placed in their roomes; for then (ſaid they) <hi>We vvill enter into the houſe of the Lord, and in his feare vvill vve vvorſhip tovvard his holie Temple.</hi> The Lord in his great mercie pitied their deſire and heard their mone. <hi>Queene Marie</hi> died: Our gracious <hi>Ladie and Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> ſucceeded, (whom almightie God long preſerue, with all health, wealth and peace to gouerne) and the booke, in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort than in former daies through <hi>Gods</hi> goodnes and hit <hi>Maiesties</hi> carefulnes (was reſtored againe. But of it now? A booke (ſaith one) blowen vp (like vnto a blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) with the wind of confuſion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation. The orders (ſaith another) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed earthly, beggarly, dungie, droſſie, louſie, Antichriſtian. The frequenting of the Lordes houſe, and worſhipping in his holy temple in his feare, vowed with the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8159:33"/>lips and promiſed with the mouth; what of it? Chriſt if hee were here on earth, ſhould not neede ſo much a whip to driue them out of the Church (ſo fewe come there) as hee ſhould neede a great ſort of whips, and that good ones to driue them thither. As for the Biſhops which they wiſhed to be remoued; <hi>mitred ones</hi> were thruſt out of their holdes ſooner than they thought; and exiles and other very zealous men placed in their ſteads. But what of thoſe then, and of their ſucceſſors now? Euen as of the Biſhops and Elders of the Churches in ſaint <hi>Pauls</hi> time: Reuiled, euill ſpoken off; made, <hi>Os perica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharmata tou coſmon,</hi> as the filth of the world, <hi>1. Cor. 4.13. Panton peripſema</hi> the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcowring of all thinges; vnto this time the very practiſe of auntient Sectaries, who by diſpraiſing and reuiling others, ſought to purchaſe fame and glorie to themſelues. But this is not all; for <hi>Captaine Cuffe of the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing band of all Surebies,</hi> the olde ſheep ebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (which pricketh at the bodie and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the fleece) will haue their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and landes to make his brats Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Their houſes muſt goe downe their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings muſt be clipped, or clean taken away, and they ſet to petrie penſions. The Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8159:34"/>with the helpe of his ſurebies <hi>(like an other Xerxes)</hi> will ſuppe vp whole countries before him, and ſnatch vp houſes and woods dales and mountaines, vallies and hills, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and all into the budget of his wrath. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocke muſt be made of the Churches inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, without contradiction either of Prince or people: els the trumpet ſoundeth <hi>à ſtylo ad macheram; Tertul. de preſcrip. pag. 110. Sect. 15.</hi> Sirs, no more words but blows and al for Church patrimony, vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of religion. <hi>Captaine Cuffe</hi> (belike in his <hi>Itinerario,</hi> or Kalender of miles) ſmelt that <hi>Abbey lands, &amp;c.</hi> ſo well pretended to be employed to the inriching of the <hi>King,</hi> maintaining of ſchooles, and releeuing the poore, were vnto ſome very ſweete, and the beſt feather of their taile; who perhaps ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpent the better part (if not the totall) vppon backe and belly, himſelfe could bee content to conſume in like proportion the remnants that are left.</p>
               <p>Heare ye this <hi>(O Elders)</hi> and hearken ye all inhabitants of this Citie, whether ſuch a thing hath beene in your daies, or yet in the dares of your fathers. The Palmer worme hath his part, and ſo hath the Graſhopper, and canker worme; and now <hi>reſiduum erucae</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:8159:34"/>the reſidue of the canker worme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Caterpiller eate if hee may. Such is the thankefulnes which theſe and others yeeld both to the Lorde, and alſo to them, who haue miniſtred and to this day doo miniſter in his ſanctified labours.</p>
               <p>It is preſuppoſed that ſome <hi>Clergie men</hi> haue too little, ſome too much, and ſome nothing at all to liue by; and therefore very requiſite that iuſt and equall diuiſion were made, that all might bee ſufficiently proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for. A deepe charity, dipped in as deep hypocriſie. But (Sirs of the corporation of Mal-contents) who ſhall make the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion?</p>
               <p>There is iuſt cauſe, why we may ſtagger at putting the Church patrimony to arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement; leſt (while diuiſion bee preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) ſome <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> adiudge the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part thereof to the <hi>Senate of Rome, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero Offic li. 10. Et ita erit nouiſſimus error peior priore;</hi> And ſo ſhall the laſt errour bee worſe than the firſt, <hi>Matthew</hi> Chapter 27. verſe, 64.</p>
               <p>But all this is the wicked working of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan the moulder of miſchief, whoſe drift hath been euermore to decay learning that there ſhould be none learned in the Scriptures, to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8159:35"/>commit the flockes vnto, which hee attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to accompliſh; Firſt by ſeducing ſpirits; Secondarily, by force of tyrants; and now laſtly, by impayring the liuings of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the worde to the intent that they (oppreſſed with pouertie) ſhould forſake the Miniſterie, &amp; ſo the little &amp; miſerable flocke of Ieſus Chriſt (left deſtitute of the foode of life) ſhould become in time, like vnto the horſe and mule which haue no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, <hi>Pſal. 32.9.</hi> In regard whereof, what good Chriſtian is there, which may not (vpon ſo iuſt occaſion) iuſtly cry out in the bitterneſſe of his heart? <hi>O tempora! O mores!</hi> O times! O manners! ſeeing the times ſo dangerous, and men in their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſo monſtrous, whome the Lorde not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>hath nouriſhed and brought vp as his children, and yet doth, but they rebell.</hi> For in what one point can they more ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantly expreſſe and make knowen their rebellion againſt the Lorde, than by batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the walls, and ſhaking the foundations of his Church? than by annoying his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts the Prophets, contrary to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement; touch not mine annointed, and do my Prophets no harme? <hi>Pſal. 105.15</hi> than by diuiding, mangling and impairing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8159:35"/>the portions of the <hi>Leuites,</hi> as in the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of <hi>Nehemiah? cap. 13. verſ. 10.</hi> which cauſed them (for that they receiued not according to the Lawe prouided in that caſe) to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the houſe of God, as not able to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the worke any longer, and to flee eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one away to his owne Land. This it was and will be when the Lords portion is pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, &amp; the mouth of the Oxe muſled that treadeth out the corne; it muſt needs breed and bring <hi>Anarchy</hi> and confuſion, euen the riune &amp; vtter ouerthrow of all good learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and true religion. For take away once the patrimonie and maintenance of the Church (at which that Axe of theirs ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth eſpecially, as at a ſweete and pleaſant roote) and intreate the Lords Ambaſſadors as <hi>Hanun</hi> did <hi>Dauids</hi> meſſengers, <hi>2. Sam. 10.4.</hi> &amp; ye take away learning; take away lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; ye take away teaching. <hi>Dauids</hi> meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers ſent to comfort <hi>Hanun,</hi> muſt of forc tarry at <hi>Iericho</hi> with ſhame inough, <hi>verſ. 5.</hi> vntill their garments bee lengthened and their beards growen; &amp; when will that be? when the children of <hi>Ammon, verſ. 6.</hi> band themſelues, and hire other to worke them (if they may) ſome further deſpite? And ſo you may lightly coniecture what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8159:36"/>of the Church of Chriſt. For, <hi>where no viſion is, the people decay, Pro.</hi> twentie nine <hi>Chap.</hi> and <hi>18.</hi> verſe. Howbeit (beloued) we hope better &amp; truſt that the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Hoasts</hi> in his accuſtomed mercye will continue a ſtrength vnto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and a defence for <hi>Iudah,</hi> yea, wee truſt that <hi>Iehouah</hi> will ſo bleſſe vs out of <hi>Zion, Pſal. 128.5.</hi> that we ſhall ſee our <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to flow with proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, peace, plenteouſnes, and true religion all the daies of our life; &amp; that the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the vineyard <hi>Pſal. 80.13.</hi> and young Vine which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath made ſo mightie and ſtrong for himſelfe, ſhall periſh in their appointed time, at the rebuke of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of our God,</p>
               <p>But if ſo be the Lords arme bee ſtretched out toward vs, if his wrath be kindled againſt vs; if matters fall out in the ende otherwiſe than well, let vs burden and blame no man but our ſelues; for wee are a crooked and rebellious nation, as badd as euer were the <hi>Iewes,</hi> if not worſe; and looke what ſinnes raigned among them <hi>Ezec. 16.49.50.</hi> and we haue exceeded them; yea, and haue iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified them, as did <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> hir two ſiſters <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Samaria, verſe, 51.</hi> in all the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations which we haue done.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:8159:36"/>
               <p>The pietie and godlines which many of vs pretend, when it is at beſt, is but <hi>Iewiſh hipocriſie,</hi> or ſome ſodaine paſſion of the minde, or violent motion, and therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth but a while; ſoone hote and ſoone cold, as was <hi>Eſaus</hi> to <hi>Iaakob, Ge. 33.4 27.41. 32.6.36.6. Sauls</hi> to <hi>Dauid, 1. Sam. 24.5.17.18. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.2.</hi> and the peoples to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which ſpread their garments in the way that hee went, which cut downe branches from the trees, which greeted him with <hi>Hoſanna, Mat. 21.8.9.</hi> and ſhortly after cried, <hi>Crucifige, crucifige eum;</hi> Crucifie him, crucifie him, <hi>Luke,</hi> 23.21.</p>
               <p>So inconſtancy in brotherly loue, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, tender mercy, kindnes, humblenes of minde, meeknes, and other ſuch liuely fruits of faith (which <hi>S. Paule</hi> biddeth vs, <hi>Coll.</hi> 3.12. <hi>as the elect of God, to put on</hi>) betrayed theſe, and ſo it betrayeth vs. Wee (as theſe men and people were) <hi>like vnto Clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water, Iude. verſe,</hi> 12. are carried about of windes, hauing no continuance in that which is good. Wee thinke that wee haue done <hi>God</hi> good and great ſeruice, when wee haue left ſome pretty ſhewes of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; though within a while after, <hi>with the Dogge we returne to the vomit,</hi> 2. Pet. 2.22.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8159:37"/>
               <p>VVe deale with the Lorde, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did with <hi>Ioſhua.</hi> How was that ſay you? Surely thus. VVe giue out many faire and large promiſes; as that all ſhalbe amended which is amiſſe; that we will do ſo and ſo no more; that wee will waxe better and better euery day. <hi>God forbid</hi> (ſay we) <hi>that we ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Lord our God, who deliuered vs when we were in miſerie, and ſcattered our enemies round about vs: therefore the Lord our God will we ſerue, and his voice will we obay.</hi> This was <hi>Iſraels</hi> vowe and promiſe then, <hi>Ioſ. 24.16.24.</hi> and the ſame is ours nowe; though quickly forgotten, as theirs was. For as they (not long after that the couenant was made, and written by <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in the booke of the law of God, and a great ſtone pitched in the remembrance and teſtimonie thereof) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the Lord to anger, ſo do we. And as did <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we haue ſaid and ſworne that we will ſerue the Lord onely, but yet marke &amp; behold, there are of vs that ſerue and follow other Gods as bad in effect, as the Gods of <hi>Aram</hi> &amp; the Gods of <hi>Zidon,</hi> &amp; the Gods of <hi>Moab,</hi> and the Gods of the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and the Gods of the <hi>Philistines, Iudg. 10.6.</hi> VVherefore, as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſaide vnto the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo giue mee leaue to ſay vnto
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8159:37"/>you, that ſay and doo ſuch things: Yee are witneſſes againſt your ſelues, <hi>Ioſ. 24.22. The ſtones of the ſtreete, which the Pauier pitched ſhall testifie againſt you;</hi> for by trampling &amp; treading on them with your feete, they are wakened, &amp; haue hard the words which ye haue ſpoken concerning the Lord.</p>
               <p>So that rather than mans diſſimulation, mans ingratitude, mans vnkindnes, mans rebellion and <hi>Apostaſie</hi> ſhall eſcape vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, the verie ſtones of the ſtreet (deafe and dumbe creatures) ſhall call and cry for vengeaunce againſt it: and who ſo is wiſe, will ponder this in his heart.</p>
               <p>Brethren, with the Apoſtle I will ſhewe you this ſecret, of which I would not that ye ſhould be ignorant, leaſt ye ſhould bee arrogant. Although it hath pleaſed God in his abundant mercie to make vs his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which in time paſt were not a people; <hi>1. Pet. 2.10.</hi> to graffe vs, a wilde oliue tree, wilde by nature, contrarie to nature in the right oliue tree, <hi>Roman. 11.17.</hi> let not the wilde oliue (though ſome of the braunches be broken off) graft in for them, and made partaker of the roote, and fathes of the <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue</hi> tree, boaſt it ſelfe againſt the branches. For if God ſpared not the naturall branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8159:38"/>take heede leaſt hee alſo ſpare not vs. Wherefore, let vs not be high minded, but feare: let vs behold the boundtifulnes &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie of God, and ponder well the one &amp; the other: toward the Iewes (which haue fallen) ſeueritie; but toward vs, bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>verſ. 22.</hi> if we continue &amp; abide therin. Beloued, theſe and ſuch like are written to warne vs, that wee ſhould beware of the like ſinnes, leaſt we feele the like plagues. Let vs remember then what manner of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple we were in time paſt, and what wee are now in Chriſt Ieſus. Let vs conſider that we haue had &amp; yet haue, a God that is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and mercifull, long ſuffering and of great compaſſion, no otherwiſe affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs than a father toward his owne children; for he hath nouriſhed and broght vs vp, thogh we haue rebelled againſt him, and yet doo. But if wee continue and goe onward, walking in the wayes of our hearts, hee will call vs to a ſharpe account, euen to the ballaunce of his iudgement <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 11.9.</hi> and becauſe hee will make due and iuſt proofe of our guiltineſſe, hee wyll ſummon the heauens and earth to witnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and the brute and dumbe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the world to condemne vs. For ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8159:38"/>doth the Lord heere againſt his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Iewes; calling to recorde agaynſt them, firſt the <hi>heauens and earth;</hi> and now (to aggrauate their ingratitude and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt him, their father) <hi>the oxe &amp; the aſſe,</hi> in this forme and manner of ſpeaking. <hi>The oxe knoweth his owner, and the aſſe his maſters cribbe; but Iſrael hath not knowen, my people hath not vnderſtand.</hi> By which kinde of compariſon, or example demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratiue, the moſt iuſt God (ſo iuſtly prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) dooth declare, that the moſt brute and dul beaſts did more acknowledge their dutie toward their maſters (which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding preſſed them downe with ſore &amp; heauie burdens) than did his people toward him, of whom they had receiued benefits without compariſon.</p>
               <p>In like ſort, the Lord in the eight chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> and the ſixt verſe complaineth of the Iewes that turned back by a perpetuall rebellion, and ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I hearkened and heard, but none ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, no man repented him of his wickednes, ſaying, What haue I done? euerie one tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their race, as the Horſe ruſheth into the battell.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:8159:39"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe 7. Euen the ſtorke in the aire know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her appointed times, and the turtle and the crane and the ſwallow obſerue the time of their comming, but my people knoweth not the iudgement of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee accuſeth the Iewes, becauſe they were more ignoraunt of the iudgements of their God, than were theſe birds of their appointed ſeaſons to diſcerne the cold and heate. But a ſtrange thing and a wonderful. They that ſhuld haue been like the Angels in heauen, that ſhould haue expreſſed, and that moſt liuely, the ſimilitude and likenes of God, are not to be preferred to the brute creatures of the earth. <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Lords inheritance, <hi>Iſrael</hi> the lot of his inheritance, <hi>Deu. 32.9. Iſrael</hi> the Lords ſeruant, <hi>Eſa. 44.21. Iſrael</hi> the Lords portion, <hi>Iſrael</hi> a thing halowed to the lord, <hi>Ier. 2.3. Iſrael</hi> the firſt fruites of the Lord, <hi>Iſrael</hi> the firſt offered to the Lord of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, <hi>Iſrael</hi> the beloued of the Lord, <hi>Eſa. 5.1.</hi> is rebellious, and as an vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heyfar; nay more than the ſtorke and the turtle, than the crane and the ſwallow: yea than the oxe and the aſſe: for the one ſort knoweth the appointed times, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his owner, and his maſters cribbe; <hi>but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8159:39"/>Iſrael hath not knowen, his people hath not vnderſtand.</hi> The oxe and aſſe are loued, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed and praiſed, not as children, but as beaſts: for beaſts they are, brute and dull. They are not preferred to anie dignitie or promotion, but laden and preſſed downe with great and waightie burdens: and yet ſee, <hi>the oxe knoweth his owner, and the aſſe his maſters cribbe;</hi> but <hi>Iſrael,</hi> vnto whome pertained the adoption, <hi>Rom. 9.4.</hi> and the glorie, and the couenants, and the giuing of the law, and the ſeruice of God, and the promiſes; of whom were the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and of whome (concerning the fleſh) Chriſte came, who is God ouer all, bleſſed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: this <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath not knowen, his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath not vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>If it had been a ſtrange people, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people, a baſtard people, a people vnknowen, a people none of his; it had not been ſo great a matter: but (ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lorde) <hi>Populus meus,</hi> my people: a people proper and peculiar vnto my ſelfe, mine owne people <hi>hath not vnderſtand.</hi> Mine owne people, which I haue choſen of old, precious in my ſight and honorable in my eyes, <hi>Eſa. 43.8.</hi> whom I haue tenderlie cheriſhed &amp; brought vp, not for their ſakes
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8159:40"/>but for mine holie <hi>Names ſake, Ezek. 36.22.</hi> whoſe fathers I led by the ſhaddow of death, <hi>Ier. 2.6.</hi> by a land that no man paſſed through, to a pleaſant and plentifull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which I gaue vnto them and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie: euen the glorious heritage of the Armies of the heathen, <hi>Ier. 3.19.</hi> This my people hath played this pranke; <hi>It will not heare nor hearken, but rebell.</hi> As a woman rebelleth againſt her husband, ſo hath my people rebelled againſt mee, <hi>Ier. 3.20.</hi> My people knoweth nothing, it hath not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand my righteouſneſſe, nor walked in the waies of my commandements, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the pathes of diſcipline, through my righteouſnes. Therefore now the Lord ſendeth <hi>Iuda</hi> his choſen and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, to the brute and dull beaſts of the earth, to the <hi>Oxe</hi> and <hi>Aſſe</hi> to learne of them knowledge, dutie, gratitude, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; which yet had the lawe of God to teach them, but would not learne; and his Prophets to call them, but would not come; and his watchmen to blow the tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet in <hi>Zion, Ier. 6.17.</hi> but they would not heare. Which vnreaſonable, brute and dul creatures of God, as the <hi>Oxe</hi> and <hi>Aſſe</hi> in this chapter of <hi>Eſay;</hi> and the <hi>Storke</hi> &amp; the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8159:40"/>
                  <hi>Turtle,</hi> and the <hi>Crane,</hi> and the <hi>Swallowe</hi> in the eight of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> ſhall one day giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence not onely againſt them, but alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs and our blindnes, except wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend; which hauing not the benefite of reaſon (but guided and gouerned onely by the inſtinct of nature) doo that which wee that haue the law of God, and teaching, &amp; diſcipline, and vnderſtanding, and reaſon, and memorie, to conceiue, iudge and beare away, will not doo.</p>
               <p>We are therefore earneſtly and heartely to praye and beſeech the Lord our God to baniſh farre from vs the ſinnes of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and vnkindnes. For (beloued) the onely recompence which the Lord dooth require at our hands for his ſundrie giftes &amp; manifold bleſſings beſtowed on vs, is this: to bee thankfull vnto him for the ſame, to feare him, to walke in his wayes, to loue &amp; to ſerue him, with all the heart, and with all the ſoule, <hi>Deu. 10.12.</hi> This is the very true &amp; perfect way to make our ſelues thankful. This hath been, is, &amp; muſt be the ſacrifice of al true &amp; perfect Chriſtians, the ſacrifice of thankſgiuing, &amp; in al things to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, &amp; ſuch is the will of God in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> toward vs; which wil of his we ought &amp; are
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8159:41"/>bound in al dutie and reuerence to imbrace &amp; obey. For let vs mortall men &amp; wormes meate, weigh well and conſider with our ſelues what God hath done for vs, as <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiodus</hi> noteth vpon the Pſalms, &amp; how great and good things he hath giuen vs for ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, preſeruation, erudition, conſolation and delight; &amp; al theſe &amp; more than theſe in his free mercie without merite: <hi>&amp; quid ni gratias agamus?</hi> and what may wee doo but giue him thankes? Thankeſ-giuing is named of <hi>Bernard (ſermon 54 ſuper cant.) Balſamum puriſsimum,</hi> the pureſt balme, and ſweeteſt ſauour in the noſthrills of our God. The Prophet <hi>Oſe cap. 14. ver. 2.</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it <hi>Vitulos labiorum noſtrorum,</hi> the calues of our lips: which, by the ſpirite of God <hi>Heb. 13.</hi> we are exhorted to offer alwaies vnto God; the ſacrifice of praiſe, the frute the lips, which confeſſe his name. Now then (as <hi>Hugo</hi> exhorteth) <hi>Si ſentis benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, redde debitum: ſi accipis benignitatem, redde charitatem.</hi> If thou feele a benefit, pay thy debt: if thou receiue liberalitie, deliuer home charitie. This we ought to doo, and this we may doo. For (as S. <hi>Auſtine in pſ. 27.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Gratias agere Deo poſſumus, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non poſſumus,</hi> Wee can giue thankes to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8159:41"/>God, but we cannot recompence him. If we might die (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>) a thouſand deaths, and powre out all the faculties and powers of the ſoule, wee can doo nothing worthie of ſuch and ſo great benifence, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and grace, which we haue receiued of God; and therefore it only remaineth that we be thankful. Let vs not flatter our ſelues leaſt we deceiue our ſelues: let vs not (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the veyle of hypocriſie) aske with the Iew <hi>Micah. 6.6.</hi> the manner and waye to pleaſe the Lord? which was conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to offer ſacrifice, but wold not change the cuſtome of his life. Let vs not contend with him, whether God will be worſhipped with bare ceremonies, without the heart? Let vs not grieue the Lord with that Iewiſh motiue: wherewith ſhall I come before the Lord, &amp; bow my ſelfe before the high God? <hi>Mic. 6.6, 7.</hi> Shall I come before him with Calues of a yere old? Wil he be pleaſed with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of rammes, or with ſtreames of oyle? Thou foole, all theſe are his, both of the forreſt, mountaines, and field, <hi>Pſal. 50.10, 11, 12.</hi> If he be hungrie, he wil not tell thee: for the world is his, and all that therein is. Offer then vnto God with <hi>Dauid Pſa. 116 17.</hi> the ſacrifice of thankeſ-giuing. For
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8159:42"/>who ſo offereth him thankes and praiſe, hee honoureth him, <hi>Pſalm. 50.23. Iſrael</hi> (to pleaſe God) would ſacrifice the firſt borne for his tranſgreſsion, euen the fruite of hys bodie for the ſinne of his ſoule, <hi>Mich. 6.7.</hi> But the Lords voice by his ſeruant the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah,</hi> calleth and cryeth better than ſo, and ſheweth thee (ô man) what is good and what he requireth of thee, <hi>verſ. &amp; ſurely to doo iustly, and to loue mercie, and to humble thy ſelfe, and to walke with thy God,</hi> in truth, and in a perfect heart, in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and obedience without hypocriſie: for the Lord hath not as great pleaſure in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, as when his voyce is obeyed, <hi>1. Sam. 15.22.</hi> To obey with him is better than ſacrifice, and to hearken is better than the fat of rammes. Rebellion (in his ſight) is as <hi>the ſinne of witchcraft, and tranſgreſsion is wickedneſſe and idolatrie.</hi> Whereby wee are taught, that the Lorde hateth nothing more than the ſinnes of ingratitude &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience; which in his owne people hee puniſhed diuers and ſundrie waies, that they might knowe and acknowledge the God that had made them, and the mightie one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that had redeemed them.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8159:42"/>
               <p>The Lord giue vs grace to amend the like faults by the correction and puniſhment of them. Happie were we, if by their harmes we could learne to beware.</p>
               <p>For (beloued) the workings of God, whether in bleſſing or afflicting, preſent or paſt, to our ſelues or others particularly, well and carefully examined, would learne vs manie a fruitefull leſſon, if wee had the grace to conſider them. S. <hi>Paul</hi> feared the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (in his firſt Epiſtle written to them, the tenth chapter and the ſixt verſe) with the examples of the <hi>Iewes</hi> paſt long before, that they ſhould not vſe the like vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they did, leaſt they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed as they were.</p>
               <p>Now let vs make thoſe examples ours: for (as the ſame apoſtle ſaith in the eleuenth verſe of the forementioned chapter) they are written to admoniſh vs alſo, whom the ends of the world are more nighly come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: that we luſt not as they luſted; that we be not idolaters, as were ſome of them; that we commit not fornication, as ſome of them committed fornication; that we tempt not Chriſt, as ſome of them tempted him; that we murmur not, as ſome of them murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; &amp; to be ſhort, that we rebel not, as ſome
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8159:43"/>of them alſo rebelled, leaſt following the like impieties wee incurre the like punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and (to our manifeſt and iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation) cauſe and procure <hi>the heauens and earth, the hils and mountaines, the rocks and mightie foundations; yea, and the beaſts of the land and the foules of the aire</hi> (before mentioned) to teſtifie againſt vs and our obſtinacie.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>heauens and earth,</hi> they in great meaſure haue already witneſſed Gods moſt heauie wrath and indignation againſt vs, &amp; that in regard of the violating of his law, &amp; contempt of his word. If theſe maye not ſerue, yet then greater tokens of his wrath than theſe, in his creatures about and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs, ſhall appeare toward vs: and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, (vnles we repent) we ſhall periſh in his iuſtice vtterly, that in his mercie refuſed to embrace him and his truth obediently. For if wee regard not the bountifulnes and loue of God our Sauiour toward vs; if wee deſpiſe the riches of his goodnes, patience and long ſuffrance, <hi>Rom. 2.4.</hi> if we contemn his word, the word of ſaluation; if the ſeed thereof ſhall not fructifie in our hearts; if the peace which we haue with God, ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der impietie; if our ciuill peace breed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8159:43"/>than beaſtly ſecuritie; if plentie work pride if with <hi>Iſrael, Num. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.6.</hi> wee loathe <hi>Manna;</hi> if we fall a luſting after fleſh, and ſet a nought the food of angels; if we tempt God, as wearie of our profeſſion; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we be waterleſſe clowdes, carried about of winds <hi>Iude ver. 12.</hi> if we be corrupt trees without frute; if we deſpiſe gouernment, and ſpeak euil of them that are in authoritie, <hi>Iude 8.</hi> if wee liue as a people caring neither for God, law nor religion; if we forſake Chriſt, and bid him farewell; if we ſit downe and fall aſleepe in the ſeate of the ſcornefull, <hi>Pſal. 1.1.</hi> if with the deafe adder we ſtoppe our eares at the voyce of the charmer, <hi>Pſa. 58 4.5.</hi> then ſhall all the bleſsings of God bee turned into curſes: the meſſage of life ſhalbe vnto vs a ſauor of death vnto death: our vineyard ſhalbe laid waſt <hi>Eſa. 5.5 6.</hi> the hedge thereof ſhalbe eaten vp, and the wall broken and troden downe; it ſhall not bee cut nor digged, but briers and thornes ſhal growe vp, and the cloudes ſhall not rayne vpon it. <hi>Deutronom. 28.37.</hi> wee ſhall bee a wonder, a prouerbe, a common talke, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, an aſtoniſhment, an hiſſing, <hi>Ier. 24 9.</hi> a curſe in all places, <hi>Ieremie</hi> the fiue and twentieth, and the ninth &amp; tenth verſes: a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8159:44"/>iuſt reward of our vnkindneſſe and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Lord, ther ſhalbe taken from vs the voyce of mirth, and the voyce of gladnes: our laughter ſhall be turned into mourning, and our ioy into ſorrow: our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wealth and pleaſure ſhall but adde a greater burden vnto our woe. Thus ſhall all the curſes of God come vpon vs, &amp; ſhall purſue vs, and ouertake vs, till we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; <hi>and that becauſe wee would not obey the voyce of our God, to keepe his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and his ordinaunces, which hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs, Deuter, 28.45.</hi> For, would the Lord plague the Citie, where his Name was called vppon, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 25.29. and ſhould we goe free? But (ô Lord God, and Father of mercies) this bee farre from vs and our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie for euer.</p>
               <p>And ſo (brethren) I will commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, <hi>Act. 20.32.</hi> which is able to builde further, and to finiſh his woorke in you, and to giue you an inheritance among all them that are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified. And withall, I giue you that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation which <hi>Ioſhua</hi> gaue to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the three and twentieth chapter and eleuenth verſe, <hi>Take good heed vnto your ſelues that ye loue the Lord your
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8159:44"/>God.</hi> And in the ſeauenth vearſe, <hi>Ioyne not your ſelues to the Gentiles; companie not with the Nations, which wander in and out among you.</hi> I meane not <hi>Perizzites,</hi> but <hi>Papists;</hi> not <hi>Iebuſites,</hi> but <hi>Ieſuites:</hi> for, as did the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes, Matth. 23.15. they compaſſe ſea and land, to make one of their profeſsion;</hi> and when he is made, they make him two-fold more the childe of hell, than they themſelues are. Wherefore (deare Brethren) beware of them: for as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> warned the Galathians in the fourth chapter and ſeauenteenth verſe, of the like ſort of men) <hi>Depereunt vos non benè,</hi> they are iealous ouer you amiſſe, euen to ſerue their owne turne; they would exclude you from the loue that you beare to GOD &amp; his truth, from the loue that ye beare to his Miniſters, who preach not themſelues, 2. <hi>Corinth. 4.5.</hi> but <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> the Lord, and themſelues your ſeruaunts for Ieſus ſake; to this end, that ye ſhuld altogether loue them and follow them.</p>
               <p>But beloued, doo not ſo. Sticke faſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord your God, as ye haue done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day. <hi>Ioſ. 23.8.</hi> Yee know in all your hearts, and in all your ſoules what and how great things the Lord hath done for ye.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:8159:45"/>
               <p>Now therefore feare the Lord, and ſerue him in vprightnes and in truth, and awaye with thoſe Gods, which your fathers ſerued beyond the floud and in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſerue ye the Lord, <hi>Ioſ. 24.14.</hi> Be not vnequally yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with the infidels. <hi>2. Cor. 6.14.</hi> the match is vnequall. Come out from among them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. and ſeperate your ſelues, &amp; touch no vncleane thing. The frute will be this: You ſhall eate your bread in plenteouſnes, and dwell in your Citie ſafely, <hi>Leuit. 26.5, 6.</hi> God will ſend peace in the land, and ye ſhall ſleepe, and none ſhall make you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid. He will couer you vnder his wings, <hi>Pſal. 91.4.</hi> and you ſhall bee ſafe vnder hys feathers: his truth ſhall be your ſhield and buckler. You ſhall not be afraid of the feare of the night, nor of the arrowe that flyeth by day: for he ſhall giue his Angels charge ouer you, <hi>verſ. 11.</hi> to keepe you in all your wayes. And this will the Lord doo for you and much more, if you feare, loue, ſerue &amp; obey him. For he will receiue you, he will be a father vnto you, and you ſhall bee hys ſonnes and daughters, <hi>2. Corinth. 6.17, 18.</hi> hee will dwell with you, and walke among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou; he will be your God, and you ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s people, <hi>Leu. 26.12.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:8159:45"/>
               <p>Finally (that I may conclude with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, with whom I began) if ye conſent and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay, ye ſhall eate the good things of the lande, <hi>Eſaie. 1.19.20.</hi> But if ye refuſe and bee rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yee ſhall be deuoured with the ſword; for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
               <p>This ſame our Lord &amp; God, who alone pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, <hi>2. Chron. 6.30.</hi> trieth &amp; ruleth the harts of the ſonnes of men, <hi>Pro. 21.2.</hi> guide vs &amp; our harts to the loue of him, <hi>1. Theſſ. 2.4.</hi> mollifie and ſoften vs, <hi>Act. 1.34.</hi> and them by the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mighty working of his holy and bleſſed ſpirit, <hi>2. Theſſ. 3.5.</hi> that we may ſenſibly feele &amp; perceiue how good and louing a God and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father hee hath beene and is vnto vs, and that we may ſhew our ſelues thankfull and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto him, liuing vnto his lawes, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing his word, and obeying his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? ſo dooing, wee ſhall be the Lords chiefe treaſure aboue all people; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he will fight for vs as he did for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> his elect &amp; choſen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; he will carrie vs on Eagles wings as he did them, throughout the dangers and troubles of this wofull <hi>Egypt,</hi> till wee come to the hauen of perfect reſt, to the land of the celeſtiall <hi>Canaan,</hi> where we ſhal haue the fruition of endles ioyes <hi>1. Cor. 2.6.</hi> which eye hath not ſeen, neither e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re hath heard, neither haue entred into the hart of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8159:46"/>man prepared of God for them that loue him. Of which ioyes God of his infinite mercie grant vs all to be partakers, through the merites and death of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his ſonne, our Lord and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; to whome with the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> triple in perſon, but one in ſubſtance, be praiſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and wiſedome, and thankes, honour, and power, and might, for euermore, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Now let vs pray.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, thou that liueſt for euer, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeſt from thy holy hill the things that are done vpon earth, heare and hearken we beſeech thee, vnto the Prayers of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and receiue into thine eares the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thy creatures. Looke not (O Lord) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the multitude of our iniquities, and haue no reſpect to the number of our ſinnes: let it not bee thy will to destroy vs which appeare worſe before thee than the Oxe and Aſſe; for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8159:46"/>the Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Masters Cribbe: but we thy children (whom thou haſt nouriſhed and brought vp as a moſt louing father) haue not knowne: and wee that in time paſt were not a people, but nowe thine owne people, haue not vnderstand. VVe muſt acknowledge and confeſſe vnto thee our Lord and God, that euen the byrdes of the Ayre, as the Storke, and the Turtle, and the Crane, and the Swallow doo better knowe and obſerue the times of their comming, then we the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thee our God. Our miſdeedes are great, and they preſſe vs downe as an heauy burden: Our iniquities are as the ſand of the ſea in number before thee. Thou haſt (O Lord) many and iuſt cauſes to doe with vs according to our offences, becauſe wee haue not kept thy commandements, neither haue walked in duty and obedience before thee, but haue rebelled as did thy people the Iewes. VVee haue the ſickeneſſe of our Fathers, wee haue done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, and dealt wickedly. Notwithſtanding (O Lord) wee truſt that thou wilt be fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and gracious vnto vs. In a contrite heart and an humble ſpirite let vs be receiued.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:8159:47"/>
               <p>Deale with vs thy ſeruants which put their truſt in thee, after thy louing kindnes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of thy mercies: ſo ſhalt thou be called mercifull, and we ſhall haue great cauſe to praiſe and glorifie thee, both for this and all other thy former benefits: ſpecially for that (as vpon this day) thou diddeſt deliuer vs and our Citie out of the handes of our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enemies and hatefull foes; which ſayd, that they would burne our dwelling places, and kill our yong men with the ſword, &amp; daſh our ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king children againſt the ground, and make our infants as a pray, &amp; our virgins a ſpoyle: which alſo ſayd, we will diuide the booty, our luſt ſhall be ſatisfied vpon them, and then wee will draw the weapon, and our hand ſhall destroy them. But thou the Lord of Hoasts, which art great and glorious, maruelous and inuincible in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whoſe voyce no creature can abide, diddeſt ſoone bring them and their deuiſes to naught. Thy right hande was glorious in power; thy right arme bruſed the enemy. In thy great glory thou diddeſt ouerthrow them that roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: thou diddeſt ſend forth thy wrath, which conſumed them as the ſtubble, and by the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8159:47"/>blaſt of thy nostrels the waters came, which ran mightily through the channels of our ſtreets, &amp; ſo drowned the labours of their hands. And ſo from that day to this (as the Egle doth her yong ones) thou haſt carried vs vppon the winges of thy mercy out of all dangers: for which and all other thy bleſsinges (moſt gracious and louing father) we ſhall from age to age remember thee and thy goodnes; this ſhall bee a feaſt day vnto vs and our posterity; we that are now, and they that are to come ſhall ſing prayſes vnto thee &amp; exalt thy name. Thou (O Lord) waſt and art our ſtrength and power, thou waſt and art our ſaluation; thou haſt beene and art our refuge, our defence, our castle, and the rocke of our might: thou art our God; thou art the God of our fathers, we will magnifie thee. And here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wee are bolde to make our deuout and harty prayers vnto thee Lord almighty and father of vs al, that thou (after thine accuſtomed mercy) wilt vouchſafe continually to remember vs, &amp; from thy holy mount to looke downe vppon vs. Keep vs (Lord) as the apple of thine eye: graue vs as another Zion, vppon the palme of thine handes, and let our walls bee euer in thy ſight.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8159:48"/>VVhen men ſhall riſe vp againſt vs, and ſhall be wrathfully diſpleaſed at vs; if wee turne to thee with all our hearts, and with all our ſoules and confeſſe thy name, and pray and make ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication before thee in this houſe, heare thou then (O Lord) in heauen, in the dwelling place of thy habitation, what prayer and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo euer ſhall bee made of any man, or of all thy people, and pardon the ſinne of thy ſeruants and bee mercifull to the tranſgreſſions of thy children; puniſh vs not according to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts; deliuer vs not whom thou haſt purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for a ſpoile vnto captiuity and death; ſell vs not into the hands of our enemies round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about vs; giue vs not ouer for a pray vnto their teeth; make vs not for a Prouerbe of reproch to the Nations farre and neere, leſt they aske, where is now their God? Let not the Heathen ſay which haue heard the fame of thee; becauſe the Lorde was not able to ſaue this people in the land that he gaue them, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hated them, therefore hee hath left them in the handes of ſpoilers to ſpoile them, and of the Nations to raigne as Lordes ouer them. (Lord) we are thy people and thine inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8159:48"/>which thou deliueredſt of olde by thy mighty power, and preſeruedſt by thy ſtretched out arme, Let this greatnes of thy power conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue; withdraw not thy accustomed fauor from vs; hide not thou thy face from vs in the time of troble, but be thou mercifull vnto vs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy great mercies: Let all the earth be filled with the brightneſſe of thy glory; let all ſuch that beare euill will at Zion, which ſeeke to lay thy vineyard waſt which thou ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly haſt planted &amp; fortified on euery part, &amp; to bring thine heritage to confuſion, be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thy great force and power, and let their ſtrength bee broken, that they may knowe that thou, which art called Iehouah, art alone, euen the moſt High ouer all the earth. Finally, (O Lorde) carry vs thy people by thy great mercie, whom thou deliueredſt; bring vs (we beſeech thee) in thy ſtrength vnto thy holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation; plant vs in the mountaine of thine inheritance, which is the place that thou haſt prepared for to dwell in, euen in the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (O Lorde) which thine handes ſhall ſtabliſh; make vs ioyfull Citizens of thy holy Citie Hieruſalem, which is aboue; goe before
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8159:49"/>vs both by day and by night in the pillar of thy fauour and goodneſſe to leade vs the way, that we may ſafely paſſe through this vale of miſery and wretchedneſſe, and finiſh this our pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage with ioy: And lastly, that (through the ayde and aſsistance of our true Ioſhua, thy ſon Ieſus Chriſt) we thy children hauing paſſed all difficulties, may reſt and dwell with thee our father in the Kingdome of all happines and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie: Euen ſo Lord Ieſus.</p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Nomb. 6.24.</bibl>
               <q>The Lord bleſſe you, and keep you; the Lord make his face to ſhine vpon you, and be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto you; the Lord lift vp his countenance vpon you, and giue you peace to your City and your ſelues now and euer, Amen.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8159:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
